<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unreasonableness of the Romanists, requiring our communion with present Romish church, or, A discourse drawn from the perplexity and uncertainty of the principles, and from the contradictions betwixt the prayers and doctrine of the present Romish church to prove that 'tis unreasonable to require us to joyn in commmunion with it.</title>
            <author>Squire, William, d. 1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15456</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11849220</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11849220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49882</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49882)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 825:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unreasonableness of the Romanists, requiring our communion with present Romish church, or, A discourse drawn from the perplexity and uncertainty of the principles, and from the contradictions betwixt the prayers and doctrine of the present Romish church to prove that 'tis unreasonable to require us to joyn in commmunion with it.</title>
                  <author>Squire, William, d. 1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38], 170 p., [1] folded plate.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Richard Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Willian Squire. cf. BM.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Relations --  Anglican Communion.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Tomkyns RR<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> 
                  <hi>in Chriſto Patri ac Domino Domino</hi> Gilbert. <hi>divina providentia Archiepiſcopo</hi> Cantuarienſi á <hi>ſacris do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticis.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>Ex Aed. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethanis <date>
                     <hi>Oct.</hi> 31.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE UNREASONABLENESS OF THE ROMANISTS, Requiring our COMMUNION With the preſent Romiſh Church: Or, a DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>Drawn from the perplexity and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Principles, and from the Contradictions betwixt the Prayers and Doctrine of the preſent <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> church; to prove that 'tis unreaſonable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us to joyn in Communion with it.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller to his moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>AFter the Aſcention of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves for the Publiſhing of the Goſpel through all the World; and where they ſaw any likelyhood of a plentifull Harveſt, they beſtowed there the greateſt Paines in the Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Chriſtian Religion. Their firſt care was for the converting of the Cities, for the greater would draw after it the leſſer; and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> ſettled in the Cities, would ſooner diffuſe it ſelf through the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent <hi>Villages:</hi> By the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:49882:3"/> their Care was the Converſion of the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> World, that from that head Religion might more opportunely be convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into all the members of that vaſt <hi>Empire;</hi> And by its Authority and Example, other Countries, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to that City, might be moved to embrace the Faith, <hi>Et cito per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vios haberet populos praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio generalis, quos unius tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Regimen civitatis</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Leo <hi>Serm. de Nat.</hi> Petri <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pauli.</note>. In the Converſion of this place both the Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>(Tertullian de praeſcriptionibus</hi> mentions alſo) <hi>S. John</hi> beſtowed their time and Labour: Here they Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, here they Suffered; <hi>quibus
<pb facs="tcp:49882:3"/> Romanis Evangelium Petrus &amp; Paulus ſanguine quoque ſuo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum reliquerunt;</hi> and both foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this Church, <hi>a glorioſiſſimis duobus Apoſtolis, Petro &amp; Paulo Romae fundatur, &amp; conſtituitur Eccleſia</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tert.</hi> adv. Marco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, li. 4.</note>. Both exerciſed here their Apoſtolical authority, and by <hi>Epiphanius Hereſ. 27.</hi> are both called Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin"> Irenae. <hi>lib. 3. cap.</hi> 3.</note>; Both of them appointed <hi>Linus</hi> to that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, <hi>Fundantes &amp; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes Eccleſiam Lino Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tradiderunt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Irenae. <hi>ibi.</hi>
               </note>. The Faith of this <hi>Roman</hi> Church was famous throughout the World, their Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings were great, for they uſually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the firſt heat of the <hi>Roman</hi> fury: Their Biſhops for the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:49882:4"/> 300 years were moſt of them Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Martyrdom; <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">De in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Li. 9. cap. 1.</note> ſaith, that ſeven only of 32 eſcaped; the <hi>Church</hi> thus foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Imperial City was moſt obſerved, and Eyed both by the Heathen, and by the Chriſtian: By the <hi>Heathen</hi> it was ſo eyed that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually it became the mark of their fury, and their Edicts of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were firſt executed in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before they were tranſmitted into the remoter <hi>Provinces:</hi> The <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> here were ſo numerous that it became the buſineſſe of <hi>7 Notaries</hi> to record their ſufferings, as <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> reports. This Church was much eyed by the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the chief City; The Faith
<pb facs="tcp:49882:4"/> of this Church like a <hi>Candle</hi> on a <hi>Hill</hi> was more conſpicuous, and its ſuffering was more obſerved than in Remoter places: The Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were commonly the moſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, like the choiceſt Soldiers, placed in the <hi>Front</hi> of the Battle: The <hi>Clergy</hi> here were very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, according to the largeneſſe of the City; for in <hi>Pontians</hi> time (which was about the year 231.) there were <hi>236 Cardinal</hi> Prieſts, as <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">D: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. cap. 9.</note> reports from <hi>Guido Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chidiaconus</hi> and <hi>Franciſcus Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barella,</hi> and theſe he explaines to be ſuch who had chiefly cure of Soules. This Church being thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced by the dignity of the City, the eminency of its founders, and the
<pb facs="tcp:49882:5"/> worth of its members, was accounted the <hi>chief</hi> Church, the Chair of <hi>Peter,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> See, and <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Theodoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith, <hi>Antiquity</hi> hath given the Biſhop of the <hi>Roman</hi> City a Principality of <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> above all. After that the World came into the Church, and the <hi>Enſign</hi> of Christianity became the Banner of the Empire, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church encreaſed in Dignity, Revenue, and Credit; for the Chriſtian <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> out of their reſpect to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, honouring the Biſhops, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their Revenue, and increaſing their Dignity, did ſhew more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular kindneſſe to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where was the <hi>Seat</hi> of their
<pb facs="tcp:49882:5"/> Empire, and which had gained ſuch esteem for the merit of its Founders. In ſhort time the Riches of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Biſhoprick or'e-topp'd the neighbouring places, the Pomp of their Biſhops was ſuitable to the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of the City: Now Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop was made the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxneſſe in Religion: Now it was decreed by the Emperours, that it ſhould not be Lawful for the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Gallia</hi> or other Provinces to attempt any thing without the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the venerable <hi>Pope</hi> of the Eternal City <note n="*" place="margin">Apud <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi> an. 445. n. 9.</note>; and in all things they haſt'ned to increaſe the Authority and Honour of that See, <hi>per omnia properamus honorem &amp; Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem
<pb facs="tcp:49882:6"/> veſtrae</hi> Sedis <hi>creſcere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Juſtinian</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. Seder. C. de. Sum. trin.</note>. But now the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which by the favour of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours,</hi> and affection of <hi>Prelates,</hi> in reverence of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Imperial Seat, had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this dignity and honour, began to ſwell with higher aimes, and to Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to greater Priviledges. If the Councel of <hi>Calcedon</hi> would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to the ſecond Patriarchſhip, upon the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as the Fathers bad dignified <hi>Rome; Propter imperium ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis illius;</hi> and would now give equal Priviledges to new <hi>Rome,</hi> judging it reaſonable that the City adorned with the Empire and Senate, ſhould enjoy equal Priviledges with
<pb facs="tcp:49882:6"/> the elder <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> Calced. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.</note>. then <hi>Leo</hi> epiſt 58. to the Empreſſe <hi>Pulcheria</hi> durſt pronounce, <hi>Conſenſiones Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ſanctorum Canonum apud Nicaeam Conditorum Regulis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantes in irritum mittimus, &amp; per authoritatem Beati</hi> Petri <hi>Apoſtoli generali prorſus defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione caſſamus,</hi> we do make the agreement of the Biſhops repugnant to the Canons of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> (for ſo he conceived the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to be) null, and by the authority of the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> do make them void. If the Councel of <hi>Sardis</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. Sardic. Can. 3. n. 8.</note> (to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the memory of S. <hi>Peter)</hi> appoints in the caſe of a Biſhop or Prieſt, that if he think he hath good reaſon why the
<pb facs="tcp:49882:7"/> cauſe ſhould be examined over again, thoſe who heard the cauſe ſhould write to <hi>Julius</hi> the Roman Biſhop, and if he think fit it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examined, that it may be ſo, and he may appoint Judges; and if he does not think it fit to be re-examined, then what he doth determine ſhall be confirmed. Or in caſe of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop depoſed, if he appeal to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Biſhop, that Biſhop if he thinks fit may write to the Neighbouring Biſhops that they determine the cauſe; and in caſe the depoſed Biſhop de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Roman Biſhop to ſend one of his Presbyters; it ſhall be in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and if he will ſend ſome with his Authority to judge the cauſe with the other Biſhops, he may do it: This
<pb facs="tcp:49882:7"/> priviledge ſhall be extended higher; that inferiour Priests may appeal to the Roman See out of any Provinces, that the cauſes of Biſhops may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>Rome</hi> and heard by him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and this profitable Authority of receiving Appeals was pretended by <hi>Zoſimus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cod. Con. Ecl.</hi> Affr. <hi>in Conc.</hi> Carth. 419.</note> from the Canons of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel, though no ſuch thing could be found in any of the Copies of that Councel in the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, as <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Atticus</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> teſtified; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this priviledge was ſo height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that all cauſes almoſt were drawn to <hi>Rome</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſperg. in Phill. lmp.</note>, all juriſdiction hindred, and cauſes were determined more according to mens gifts than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir rights. If the Antients did
<pb facs="tcp:49882:8"/> ſhow any reſpect to the <hi>Roman</hi> See, allowing it the priviledge to be the first Seat, and that Biſhop to be firſt of all Prieſts, ſo <hi>Juſtinian</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Nov. 131. Cap. 2.</note> deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines according to the ancient Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, that he be the chiefeſt of Biſhops and the firſt Patriarch, and have the firſt place in Councels before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Patriarchs; and i'le add ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther priviledge, which Pope <hi>Julius</hi> mentions <note n="*" place="margin">Socrat. <hi>li. 2. Cap.</hi> 13.</note> as an Eccleſiaſtical Law, that without the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop no decrees ſhould be made in Councels: Now theſe priviledges ſhall be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded higher, that all other Patriarchs ſhall be his Subjects <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>D</hi> st. 22. Ca de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant.</note>, that by divine right the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is head of the Church, <hi>Caput &amp; Cardo à Domino, &amp; non ab alio Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolica
<pb facs="tcp:49882:8"/> Sedes conſtituta eſt, &amp; ſicut cardine oſtium, ſic hujus Apoſtolicae Sedis authoritate omnes Eccleſiae reguntur</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Dist. 22. c. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Ecl. <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </note>. That it is of neceſſity to Salvation for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Humane Creature to be under the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, ſaith <hi>Boniface</hi> (who lived 1294.) in the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na. de major. &amp; Obed.</note>. If the Ancient Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him the priviledg to ſee the Canons of the Church put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as the firſt Seat to ſee that the Laws made by general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be Obſerved: This Law ſhall be extended higher, that he may diſpenſe with the Laws made by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels, unleſſe it be in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith <note n="†" place="margin">Cauſ. 25. Qu. 1.</note>; That no Councel can put Bounds to his power, as <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49882:9"/> the Second (who was Pope 1099.) Bragged, that if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil ſhould add any <hi>Clauſa irritans virt.</hi> Should declare all diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be Null, and Invallid which are contrary to their Canons; yet the Pope hath power to diſpenſe in thoſe caſes, as <hi>Victoria</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lact. 4. de pot. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae N. 4. prop. 4.</note> ſaith. Again if the Ancients did account the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be the Teſt of Orthodoxneſſe in Religion, as <hi>Hierom</hi> tells <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> I following no Chief but Chriſt, am joyned in Communion to thy Bleſſedneſſe, that is to the Chair of <hi>Peter,</hi> and he that gathereth not with thee Scatereth, that is, who is not <hi>Chriſt's</hi> is <hi>Antichriſt's,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Church at that
<pb facs="tcp:49882:9"/> time was free from thoſe Hereſies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church had groaned, and therefore if they joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Roman,</hi> it was a ſign that they Renounced the Errors which afflicted the <hi>Eaſtern;</hi> and ſo it was Required by the Emperours <note n="*" place="margin">L. cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos C. de Sum. trin.</note>, that all ſhould profeſſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which it appeared that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> follow, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Diſcipline of the Apoſtles and the Doctrine of the Goſpel, we believe <hi>one Deity of the Father, Son, and Holy-Ghoſt.</hi> Now what they ſpake of the preſent time, the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops pretend to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant priviledges of that See; for they loſt no time to inhanſe their
<pb facs="tcp:49882:10"/> own greatneſſe: <hi>Leo</hi> was hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at it, <hi>Hactenus fides Petri non defecit,</hi> hitherto it hath not failed; and he adds, <hi>Nec defectura Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur in Throno ſuo</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Leo.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. 9. ad Pat. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och.</note> that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church neither hath Erred, nor ſhall Err <note n="†" place="margin">Greg. 7. <hi>li. 2. post. Ep.</hi> 55.</note>: and in diſſention about matters of faith, be that ſhall take that ſide to which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> adheres, ſhall be ſecure, for Chriſt hath prayed that <hi>Peters</hi> faith faile not. The firſt ground of the priviledg, was becauſe that the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Chriſtian Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that point, was preſerved ſincere in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: For the Emperours ſay they would have all the people to profeſſe that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>S. Peter</hi> delivered to the
<pb facs="tcp:49882:10"/> 
               <hi>Romans,</hi> and which it appears Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> followed; This after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Popes</hi> claim, as the fruits of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Prayer for <hi>S. Peter,</hi> and the priviledge of their See. By theſe Steps the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop aſcended to that height of Power he enjoyed, what was either by conſent or Cuſtom, either in honour of <hi>S. Peter</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Imperial Seat, either for the greatneſſe of the City, the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of many Biſhops, or the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxneſſe in Religion (while the World groaned under <hi>Arianiſme)</hi> aſcribed to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, was afterwards challenged to be due by Divine right. Then the <hi>Siſter</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged to be the <hi>Mother,</hi> the <hi>fellow-Servant</hi> to be the <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> of all
<pb facs="tcp:49882:11"/> Churches, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop who was ſo often called by <hi>Cyprian</hi> his <hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>Collegue,</hi> to be in effect the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter:</hi> The Canons were trodden under foot, the Authority of Biſhops depreſt, and all things brought into confuſion, his flatterers, and thoſe that thrived by his greatneſſe labouring ſtill to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Power; they cried him up to have <hi>Omnia jura in ſcrinio pectoris,</hi> all Laws contained in his Breſt <note n="*" place="margin">Const. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emp. ord. gloſs. in C. 2. expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe. Lanc. init. jur. Canon. L. 1. tit. 3. de Eccl. Conſt.</note>, that he was above all Laws, and his bare will a ſufficient Reaſon, and his decretal Epiſtles were equal not only to the Canons of general Councils, but they were alſo Reckoned among the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scriptures, and yet this Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
<pb facs="tcp:49882:11"/> ſaying fathered on <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin lib. 2. de Doctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Distinct 19. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicis.</note>, is not expunged either by <hi>Thomas Manriques</hi> when he ſet forth the cenſures on the gloſſes by command of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> or by <hi>Sixtus Faber</hi> Mr. of the Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Pallace, in his Cenſures pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by command of <hi>Greg. 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 1580.</hi> nor did he only challenge a primacy in Spirituals, but even in Temporals as <hi>Bonif. 8.</hi> in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant <note n="†" place="margin">Extrar. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. de. major. &amp; obedient.</note> ſaith, that in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Power are two Swords, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and the Temporal, and ſo Pope <hi>Nicolas</hi> tells the <hi>Milanois,</hi> that God gave to <hi>Peter</hi> the Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper of Eternal life, <hi>Terreni ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul &amp; coeleſtis Imperij curam,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49882:12"/> That he ſhall take the charge of the Earthly and Heavenly Empire, and from hence the gloſſe <note n="*" place="margin">Gloſſ. in Coelest. dist. 22. omnis.</note> Argues, that the Pope hath both the Spiritual and Temporal Sword. Or if this Power ſeem to be too extravagant, yet to this day he challengeth a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>indirecte &amp; in ordine ad Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia,</hi> over Temporal things, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he do not pretend to a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect dominion; as if all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Earth were only his Vaſſals, and held their Dominion in Fee of him; for Princes are grown Wiſer than to have their Crowns ſo eaſily ſpurn'd off their heads, yet he hath as full a power over all things by this pretence of <hi>indirecte &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad Spiritualia;</hi> and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:49882:12"/> 
               <hi>Victoria</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Relact. 1. de. pot. 1 e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.<hi>N.</hi> 12.</note> calls it <hi>Ampliſſimam poteſtatem:</hi> for he can both when, and how much he thinks it neceſſary in order to Spiritual things, make and unmake Princes, divide Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, and do many other things of the like ſort, as <hi>Victoria</hi> add's: And that he hath the ſupream Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in temporal things, all grant him ſaies <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Riſposta del Card. <hi>Bellar.</hi> a'l 3a prop. di. Giou. Marſelio.</note> except the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, <hi>tutti lo Concedono, ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetto g'l Heretici:</hi> and the only difference in theſe Authors Opinions is in the manner how he hath this Power; Some think he hath it as Temporal Princes have it: Others think that the Power of the Pope is properly and in it ſelf Spiritual, but in order to ſpiritual affaires may
<pb facs="tcp:49882:13"/> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dle with temporal things with moſt full Authority, <hi>con pieniſſima Autorita;</hi> and if it be profitable for Chriſtianity, may diſpoſe of the kingdoms and Empires of Chriſtians as they have done very oft; thus he concludes the anſwer to the <hi>third Propoſition.</hi> When the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were come to this greatneſſe Kings muſt hold their ſtirrups, the Emperour muſt bring the Water when the Pope waſheth, he muſt pour it out, he muſt bring the first diſh, if Princes will be ordered by their Mr. of Ceremonies <note n="*" place="margin">Sacr. Coerem. l. 1. tit. 3.</note>: then the Biſhops began to uſe the Imperial Robes, then they ware a triple Crown, in ſign of his Empire he weares an Imperial Crown, in ſign that he is
<pb facs="tcp:49882:13"/> Pope he uſeth a Miter <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Durand.</hi> Ration. div. offic. l. 3. c. 17.</note>, and in all great proceſſions the ſame Honour is ſhowed to him which was wont to be uſed to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dur.</hi> ibi in fine.</note>; at the mention of his Name in their Prayers for the Pope, the Priests muſt bow their Heads <note n="*" place="margin">Miſs. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tub. celeb. miſs. c. 5. de Oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. <hi>n.</hi> 2.</note>, His feet muſt be kiſſed both by Princes and Prelates, <hi>ſolius Papae pedes om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes deoſculentur</hi> is <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>'<hi rend="sup">s.</hi> dictate <note n="†" place="margin">L. 2. post. Ep. 55.</note>. Much more of their Pride and Vanity might be reckoned up, even while they pretended the Humility to be the ſervants of ſervants; and what care of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can be expected in them, who every day ſtudied to advance their own greatneſſe, and to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above the Height of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:49882:14"/> Monarchs? How can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that Tares ſhould not be ſown, when thoſe who pretended to be the Watch-men ſlept? How can we judg the purity of Religion to have been preſerved, when the pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Learning of the Clergy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and Pride, Covetouſneſs, and Ambition increaſed? The weeds were grown up though few obſerved when they firſt peeped out of the ground, after-ages ſaw Tares had almoſt covered the Corn, but the World was too buſie in Contentions about greatneſſe and honour to mind the firſt ſprouting of them: It was the frequent complaint of Pious men, that abuſes were crept into the Church, and that there needed a
<pb facs="tcp:49882:14"/> Reformation <hi>in Capite &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris,</hi> they complained of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Canons, and abundance of Ceremonies: <hi>Multae Conſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Praeſulum, de quibus non ſine cauſa eſt publica Orbis quaerela, &amp;c.</hi> There are many Conſtitutions of Prelates, which are justly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by the World, there are in many Churches ſuperſtuous, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and ſuperſtitious Ceremonies ſaies <hi>Eraſmus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Declar. ad Cens.</hi> Paris n. 58.</note>. Many complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the vain and ſuperſtitious uſe of Reliques and Images: <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtius eſt quam ut multis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicari verbis debeat, imaginum cultum &amp; ſimulachrorum ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium invaluiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> It is too plain, that the worſhip of Images had
<pb facs="tcp:49882:15"/> too much increaſed, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather ſuperſtition of the People was too much indulged; ſo that our men did ſeem to omit nothing of that high adoration given by the <hi>Pagans</hi> to their <hi>Statues,</hi> or of the extream vanity which they allowed in making, and worſhiping of their Images, as <hi>Caſſander</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note n="*" place="margin">Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio. tit. de imagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bns.</note>; great were the abuſes which were crept into the Church in the Prayers to <hi>Saints,</hi> in the immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Prayers of the Bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> in the chooſing oſ particular <hi>Patron-Saints,</hi> in their proceſſions, Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, over-valuing of monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal habits, in their Faſts, in their Prayers, in their <hi>Legends</hi> of Saints lives, in their forging of miracles,
<pb facs="tcp:49882:15"/> Revelations, and Stories which might ſerve to increaſe the Prieſts profits. Great were the Abuſes in the Popes Exorbitant power, in his proviſions, reſervations, diſpenſations, exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exactions, indulgencies, &amp;c. T'is needleſſe at preſent to reckon up all the abuſes both in Doctrine and diſcipline, ſome complaining of one thing, ſome of another, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding there was a neceſſity of a Reformation: But how ſhould it be effected when the great diſeaſe lay as it were in the head? Little could be expected from general Councils, when they neither could now be called without the Popes conſent, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Valid without his Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when the Biſhops ſtiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb facs="tcp:49882:16"/> 
               <hi>Dei &amp; Apoſtolicae Sedis gratia Epiſcopi:</hi> When they had not only ſworn Canonical obedience to him, which is alwaies underſtood, <hi>in Licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> in things which were honeſt, and allowed by the Canons; But an Oath of fealty as their <hi>Ceremoniale Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cerem. Epiſ. tit. de pallio.</note> calls it, that they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend <hi>Regalia ſancti Petri,</hi> the Royalties of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> under which he comprehended many of his uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations: Little could be expected from the Biſhops in their ſeveral Dioceſſes, ſince all were now depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants on the <hi>Pope,</hi> and if they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the incroachments on their rights, or the innovations ſtealing into the Church, the Pope preſently
<pb facs="tcp:49882:16"/> threatned, <hi>concutere candelabrum eorum,</hi> to ſhake their Candleſtick, as <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">William Thorn <hi>Chron. in Sylvist. Allat. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> 1153.</note> Writ to <hi>Theobald</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury:</hi> Then they muſt anſwer for it at <hi>Rome,</hi> where the uſual confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was by fire and faggot. At length the wiſe providence of God opened a way to a Reformation in many Countries; if in ſome places the proceedings were ſomewhat tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, I juſtify not the faults of any, but only acknowledg the bleſſing which God hath beſtowed, who can bring good out of evil. At home the Reformation was begun by conſent of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> Spiritual and Temporal, the Approbation of the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> the determination
<pb facs="tcp:49882:17"/> of the <hi>Convocation:</hi> Thus it was carried on in the reign of his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor <hi>Edward 6<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </hi> When it was re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> it was in a regular way, by a legal ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of thoſe Statutes made in Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> time, and the Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of the Lawes made by King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> with Synodical conſent: All which things are fully and Satisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily handled by Sir. <hi>Roger Twiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Heylin;</hi> after the Re. eſtabliſhment of the Reformation by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> there were few or no Recuſants known in <hi>England</hi> for many years, as is conſtantly avouched by our Writers, who lived near thoſe times, few of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion (if at any time they went
<pb facs="tcp:49882:17"/> to <hi>Maſs)</hi> refuſed to be preſent at our ſervice <note n="*" place="margin">Lord Cokes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>barge as <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1606.</note>; and when afterwards <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Quintus</hi> by his <hi>Bull,</hi> had forbid thoſe whom he called <hi>Catholicks</hi> to reſort to our <hi>Prayers,</hi> there appeared only few who adhered to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion; the Popes laboured hard to keep up their party here, by foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Seminaries for the instructing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> youth abroad, and by frequent Miſſions of Prieſts hither, to propagate and Defend the Romiſh Doctrine; yet during the reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, Popery decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; till the troubles of our late warrs gave the Romiſh emiſſaries opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to pervert many unſtable perſons, who either diſcontented with their
<pb facs="tcp:49882:18"/> ſufferings at home, or pinched with neceſſity, or offended with the many Sects which the licentiouſneſſe of Warr had begot, or couzened with pretenſes of the <hi>Antiquity, unity, glory,</hi> and <hi>ſplendor</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, or perhaps allured with the pleaſing Doctrine and Opinions, whereby many Romiſh <hi>Caſuiſts</hi> gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie Sinners, revolted from us; and whether the reſtauration of Peace and Order may reclaim thoſe, whoſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and troubles alienated from us, God only knowes; There is great talk still of the increaſe of <hi>Popery,</hi> (the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtriving to credit their cauſe by theſe reports of numerous <hi>Proſelites)</hi> though I hope it is not ſo, as I ſee no reaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:49882:18"/> ground that it ſhould be ſo; yet the reports of Enemies ſhould at leaſt alarum us to be as Active in maintaining our ground, as they are in ſtriving to gain it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we are weary of our Religion, to ſhew as much zeal in defending, as they do earneſtneſs in aſſaulting; This hath Occaſioned the enſuing Diſcourſe, in which my deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gn is from the doubtfulneſs and perp'ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctrine, the Superſtitious vanity of many allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed prastiſes in their Church, the abſurdities in their publique Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and the contradictions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Prayers and Doctrins to diſſwade the fond Admirers of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb facs="tcp:49882:19"/> to reclaim them who are ready to embrace their Errors for Catholick truth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:20"/>
            <figure>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>SSIVS MOLNA S. IGNATIVS LOYOLA SOCIETATIS IESV FVNDATOR. VASQUEZ ESCOBAR</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Optabilir eſt Fur qua'm Mendax aſsiduus; vtri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> veró Perditionis hareditatem conſequentur. Eccles. 20 vers. 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49882:20"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The firſt <hi>Conſideration</hi> I propoſe, ſhall be from the doubtfulneſſe, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty of many Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not Reaſonable to Adhere to that Church, which Commands us to believe (under pain of damnation) Doctrines which are uncertiane and dubious: But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth Require ſuch things; <hi>pro.</hi> In the Creed of <hi>Pius</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bulla <hi>Pij 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Super form. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ: fid.</note> There are ſeveral things Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired as Conditions of Communion with that Church, and which their Clergy are bound to ſwear that they truly Believe, and will conſtantly defend, and that they will take Care
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49882:21"/> that they be taught to, and Believed by thoſe who are under their Charge, and this alſo they Acknowledge to be the <hi>Catholick</hi> faith, without which there is no Salvation: But now many of theſe things (which they are Bound to hold according to the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Decree (are Uncertain and Doubtfull, and from their own Principles and Confeſſions will apear ſo.</p>
            <p>1. I inſtance in the <hi>Artic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> that they acknowledge <hi>the holy Catholick Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Roman Church to be the Mother and Miſtriſſe of all Churches:</hi> But there is no Certainty of the truth of this Article, for it is either meant of the Churches united under the Obedience of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, or elſe of the Particular Dioceſs of <hi>Rome:</hi> It cannot be meant of the Univerſal Church which obeyes the Univerſal Vicar of Chriſt, as <hi>Suarez</hi> phraſeth it: for all Churches are ſuppoſed by them mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Univerſal Church, and the Univerſal Church to be the Coll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ection of all Churches: Now it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49882:21"/> to call the Univerſal Church A <hi>Mother</hi> of all Churches, for all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are the ſame with the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal</hi> Church, and nothing can be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Mother</hi> to it ſelfe; Again, it cannot be a <hi>Miſtriſſe</hi> of all Churches, for it is only a Society of all Churches United together; and Suppoſe all thoſe Churches throughout the world, of which this Univerſal Church is made, I aske what is the <hi>Miſtriſſe</hi> to all theſe Churches? either tis the <hi>Roman</hi> particular Church which I ſhall ſhew to be otherwiſe, or elſe they muſt ſay that all theſe Churches United are a <hi>Miſtriſſe</hi> to all Churches, when yet they ſuppoſe no other can be a Church but what is United with theſe, which is abſurd. If they mean the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Roman</hi> Church, then firſt, that cannot be a <hi>Mother</hi> of all Churches, which in order of time was founded after ſome Churches, unleſſe wee could ſay the <hi>Mother</hi> might be born after the <hi>Daughter,</hi> but the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was founded after the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and therefore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49882:22"/> St. <hi>Hierome</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Com. in Iſſ. 2.</note> ſayes, the Church foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> begat the Churches of the whole world, <hi>Eccleſia in Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem fundata totius orbis Eccleſias ſeminavit,</hi> and the <hi>Synodical</hi> Letter <note n="*" place="margin">Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cl. Hist. l. 5. 6. 9.</hi>
               </note> from the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to <hi>Damaſus</hi> and the <hi>Weſtern Biſhops</hi> calls <hi>Cyril,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of all Churches: Again, the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was founded af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the <hi>Diſciples</hi> were firſt called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts II. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Quae prima omnium auſa eſt proferre Chriſtianum nomen, atque Naſcentis Evangelij gloriam praedicare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum l. 4. c. 2.</note> I may ad, after the Church of <hi>Britaine,</hi> for <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Defenſ. Fidei Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. l. 1. c. 1.</note> confeſſeth, it was from the firſt Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Goſpel, and <hi>Baronius</hi> from ſome manuſcripts in the <hi>Vatican</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixeth it to the 35th year of our Lord, which was near nine years before the founding of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; If then the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after ſome other Churches, it is then uncertain and doubtful how we can acknowledg it to be the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49882:22"/> of all Churches, and proſeſſe this as an <hi>Article</hi> of Faith without which there is no Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If it be not <hi>de fide</hi> that the <hi>Roman</hi> particular Church ſhall never err in matters of Faith, then it is abſurd to make this profeſſion alwaies, that ſhe is the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches, for that cannot alwaies be the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches, which may ceaſe to be a member of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church: But even by their own confeſſions, it is not <hi>de fide</hi> that the <hi>Roman</hi> particular Church ſhall alwaies remain, or alwaies adhere to the true faith: for that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be the Seat of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of many <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> and if it be <note place="margin">Ribera <hi>&amp;</hi> Viega <hi>in Apoc. 17.</hi>
               </note> the Seat of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> it is uncertain how it can remain the Miſtreſs of all Churches; again, that it ſhall not fail, it is only <hi>pia &amp; probabiliſſima opinio</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>l. 4. de</hi> Rom. <hi>pont. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> But not ſo certain that the contrary can be called <hi>Heretical,</hi> or manifeſtly erroneous; yea, there is no promiſe (if we look on that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49882:23"/> Church preciſely) that it ſhall never revolt from the <hi>Catholick</hi> faith, ſaies <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fid. Cathol. l. 1. 5. 5.</note> Now if it be not <hi>de fide</hi> that the <hi>Roman</hi> particular Church ſhall never err in matters of faith, and that there is no promiſe to ſupport it from failing, then 'tis abſur'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs alwaies this <hi>Article</hi> as neceſſary to Salvation, <hi>That ſhe is the Mother and Miſtreſſe of all Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſhall ſay that the particular Church, taken abſtractly from its Biſhop may err, but conſidered as united with its head the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Biſhop then it can never err, or fall away, <hi>propter Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedram Petri praeſidentem,</hi> ſaies <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Defenſ. fid. Cathol. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> l. 1. c. 5. n. 6, 7.</note>; for the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop is the <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of the whole Church, the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Teacher</hi> of all Chriſtians, to whom in St. <hi>Peter</hi> was delivered the full power of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and governing the univerſal Church, as the <hi>Florentine</hi> Council determines: ſo that whatſoever Church is in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with him, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the priviledg derived to him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49882:23"/> by St. <hi>Peter</hi> cannot fall into any error, <hi>hoc habet quaelibet alia Eccleſia ſub ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ratione &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nione ſpectata,</hi> ſaies <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Defenſ. fid.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ibi.</hi> n. 6.</note>: But now if the foundation of this Article be doubtful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, it will follow that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle it ſelf is doubtful and uncertain alſo. Firſt then, (ſetting aſide the queſtion about St. <hi>Peters</hi> univerſal Paſtor-ſhip which contains many perplexities) it is uncertain, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be by <hi>Divine right</hi> a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to that univerſal Paſtor-ſhip, for there is no mention in Scripture of a ſucceſſor, no Command to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point one, and no evident conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that any ſuch was appointed; and if there can be no certain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand produced to appoint a ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, nor evident conſequence that by <hi>divine</hi> Command any ſuch was appointed, then it is uncertain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be by <hi>divine</hi> right a ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor to that univerſal Paſtor-ſhip. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is uncertain whether thoſe priviledges which our Saviour obtained by his Prayer for St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49882:24"/> are to be extended to his Succeſſor, for either all muſt be allowed to a Succeſſor, or only ſome priviledges: if all priviledges, then the Succeſſor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> can neither err in his own judgment, nor teach any error to others: But this is more then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves require, for the former privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg <hi>fortaſſe non deſcendit ad poſtelos,</hi> perhaps it hath not deſcended to his ſucceſſors, ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">l. 4. de <hi>Rom.</hi> Pont. c. 3.</note> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Loc. <hi>Com. lib. 6. c. 8.</hi>
               </note> gives the account of <hi>Pighius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Popes (by vertue of this Prayer) being free from perſonal er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror: <hi>Quamvis in multis locis dicit ſatis probabiliter de ſummi Pontificis autoritate, tamen non id ſpectandum quid dicit, ſed quid conſentaneum ſit ei dicere,</hi> though he ſpeaks probably enough in many places of the Popes authority, yet that is not ſo much to be regarded what he ſaies, as what is fit for him to ſay, &amp;c. for he adds in another place, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but the Pope may be an <hi>Heretick:</hi> If only ſome priviledges were here given to his ſucceſſor, as <hi>infallibility</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49882:24"/> in Doctrine, that he ſhould never teach error, <hi>tanquam Pontifex,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our Saviour obtained for St. <hi>Peter</hi> the priviledg of perſevering in ſaving faith, and alſo infallibility in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: I demand then, where hath our Saviour diſtinguiſh't betwixt the priviledges here given to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and to his Succeſſors? Where is it ſaid what he hath obtained for the one, and what he hath obtained for the other? Where are thoſe words about Teaching, or Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others? or that a Succeſſor ſhould teach no errors, any more then St. <hi>Peter</hi> could? to ſum up this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there can be no pretence that the priviledges procured for St. <hi>Peter</hi> belonged to his Succeſſors without our Saviours grant, but 'tis uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whether there be ſuch a grant; for either all priviledges muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to his Succeſſors, which is more then they would have: or there muſt be ſome diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe priviledges which he procured for St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49882:25"/> he obtained for his ſucceſſors; but if there be none to be found there, as I have ſhewn, then it follows that it is uncertain whether the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges which our Saviour obtained for St. <hi>Peter</hi> are to be extended to his Succeſſors. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> granting there be a ſucceſſor, yet ſtill this <hi>Article</hi> that <hi>the Biſhop of Rome is the ſucceſſor of St. Peter</hi> (I mean in that large ſenſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> take it) is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and doubtful; for there is no Command extant that S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould fix his Seat at <hi>Rome,</hi> and no Divine Teſtimony that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was appointed his ſucceſſor; and if there be neither Command that he ſhould be appointed his ſucceſſor, nor Divine Teſtimony that he was ſo appointed, it follows then that this Article, <hi>The Biſhop of Rome is St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's ſucceſſor,</hi> is uncertain and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; if there were a Command, then either it was given before St. <hi>Peter</hi> would have departed from <hi>Rome,</hi> or after his return thither again: if before St. <hi>Peters</hi> going out of Rome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49882:25"/> he received the command to fix his Seat there then it is not likely that he would have offered to remove thence which (as the ſtories quoted by <hi>Bellarmin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">l. 1. de <hi>Rom.</hi> pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 23.</note> ſay) was a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Death: if after his return to <hi>Rome</hi> he received this Command, how does it appear, yea that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch Command either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his offering to depart, or after his return? what <hi>Record?</hi> what <hi>Teſtimony?</hi> what aſſurance of any ſuch thing? if there were a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, then either that Teſtimony is <hi>Divine,</hi> or <hi>Humane;</hi> if it be a <hi>Divine</hi> Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony let it be produced; if it be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Humane</hi> Teſtimony, then it makes only a <hi>Humane</hi> faith, and therefore it can be no Article neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be believed on pain of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor. Again that which is not yet agreed on by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctors, whether it be by Divine, or Humane right, cannot be made
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49882:26"/> by them a <hi>Fundamental</hi> Article of faith: But by what ground the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſucceeds to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> is not yet agreed on by them poſitively. Some ſay it is only by <hi>Humane</hi> right, ſo <hi>Soto Armacanus,</hi> and <hi>Paludanus,</hi> as <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">de trip. Vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. diſp. 10. ſſ. 3. n. 9.</note> tells us; Some ſay it is not by <hi>Divine</hi> right, <hi>Sed ex facto &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Petri</hi> ſaies <hi>Azorius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Inst. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. part. 2. l. 4. c. 11.</note>: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeaks very perplexedly, it is not <hi>ex prima inſtitutione quae legitur in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelio</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell.</hi> l. 2. de <hi>Rom.</hi> pont. c. 12. § at. vero § at. quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Sobs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 4. c. 4. ſſ. at ſetun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum §. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeo ſſ. accedit.</note>: not from the firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution which is in the Goſpel, but then we would find the ſecond inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, It is not (ſaies he) impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the Lord plainly Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. Again peradventure it is not by Divine right, although it pertain to the Catholick faith: Again it is not altogether <hi>de fide</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Seat cannot be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: Again <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not plainly Command it, but is ſaid to Command it, becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> did tranſlate his Seat thither by Gods inſpiration: Again it does not appear how Chriſt Commanded
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49882:26"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> that he ſhould place his Seat, poſ. it is not <hi>de fide</hi> that the See of <hi>Rome</hi> was eſtabliſhed by a <hi>Divine</hi> and immutable Command: Thus they are perplext where to found this right of ſucceſſion, and poſ. this propoſition the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is St <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor muſt be even in their apprehenſion doubtful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain: <hi>Laſtly,</hi> thoſe who pretend a <hi>Divine</hi> right, confeſs that it is not expreſs'd in Scripture, but only virtually contained in the principles revealed in it, for (ſaies <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Defenſ. fid. Cathol. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c 13. n. 5.</note>) <hi>There was a primacy given to Peter, and that primacy was to laſt in the Church, and this muſt be a Succeſſion of Perſons in the ſame dignity, now the application of this Inſtitution and dignity to this particular Biſhoprick, is ſufficiently evidented by plain Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and evident uſe.</hi> But this is wholly uncertain; for firſt, where ſhall we find this <hi>Tradition</hi> that St. <hi>Peter</hi> appointed the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop his ſucceſſor. Secondly, where ſhall we find that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49882:27"/> be his ſucceſſor becauſe he died Biſhop of <hi>Rome?</hi> for there is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that St. <hi>Peter</hi> diſpoſed his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Biſhoprick to that See where he died, nor any certainty from the Nature of the thing, that it muſt fall to that place where he died; nor any certainty that the See which he laſt held hath any more priviledg on this account, than the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> where hefirſt ſate: nor any certainty that the power of naming a ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor did not fall to the Apoſtles who ſurvived him, or to the Univerſal Church: till theſe things be certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined, it remaines ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>It is uncertain whether this or that particular Biſhop of Rome be the true Biſhop of Rome,</hi> and <hi>pro.</hi> uncertain whether he be St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor; and <hi>pro.</hi> higher ſtill, it is uncertain whether he hath the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges obtained by our Saviour for St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors; and higheſt of all, whether the <hi>Roman</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49882:27"/> Church, or any other is ſecured from Error by being ſubject to him: It is neceſſary <hi>de fide</hi> (ſaies <hi>Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Di trip. Virtute diſ. 10. ſect. 5. n. 2.</note>) that this man who is received by the common conſent of the Church, as head of it, to which it is bound to obey, is the <hi>true</hi> Pope and ſucceſſor of St. <hi>Peter:</hi> The reaſon he gives is this, <hi>For it will be impoſſible, otherwiſe to believe certainly what he defines;</hi> the ſame thing <hi>Salmero</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In Epista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las <hi>Pauli</hi> in genero part. 3. diſp. 2. p. 133.</note> ſpeaks <hi>that with ſame faith with which we believe Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, we alſo believe Paulus fourth to be the Pope: Non tantum huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fide cui poſſit ſubeſſe falſum:</hi> But now if this be uncertain then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>de fide,</hi> and that it is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain appears thus. Firſt, there may be <hi>Schiſmes</hi> in the Papacy, as hath been often (ſince the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick became rather a Dignity than an Office; one Schiſme laſted 50 years <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Onuph. in Vita</hi> Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban. 6.</note>; ſometimes three Popes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as <hi>Bened.</hi> 13. <hi>Greg.</hi> 12. <hi>John</hi> 23. all of them pretended themſelves to be the true Vicars of Chriſt, all of them as true Popes created Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49882:28"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Platina <hi>in Vita</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. 5.</note>, and were allowed for Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals by the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Onuph. <hi>in Vita</hi> Greg. 12.</note>, and electors of the ſucceeding Popes, the Cardinals of <hi>Greg.</hi> 12. and <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</hi> 13, created <hi>Alexander</hi> the fifth in the Councils of <hi>Piſa;</hi> the Cardinals of theſe <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Popes (of which ſome had been made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals after the depoſition of theſe Popes at <hi>Piſa)</hi> were electors of <hi>Martin</hi> the fifth; either then they were all true Popes, or none of them, <note place="margin">Onuph. <hi>ibi.</hi>
               </note> or onely one of them: they were not all true Popes, according to the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who tell us, there is but one <hi>Legitimate</hi> ſucceſſor, the reſt are <hi>Rebells</hi> and <hi>Tyrants:</hi> if onely one was true Pope, then thoſe Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls which the Antipopes crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, could not be lawfull Cardinals, nor lawfull Electors of the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Popes; nay, nor according to an Ancient conſtitution could be Popes themſelves: and yet <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4th was created Cardinal by <hi>Greg.</hi> 12th whom they confeſſe was a Schiſmatical Pope: if none of theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49882:28"/> were true Popes, then for fifty years it was not neceſſary <hi>de fide</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this or that man to be true Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> nor was it certain that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was the Miſtreſs of all Churches, becauſe of its conjunction with the ſucceſſor of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſince all that time it was uncertain who was the true ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. Secondly, it is uncertain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be no ſecret impediments, which hinder him from being true Pope, as whether the eſſentials re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the election and conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pope be rightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and pro. it cannot be <hi>de fide</hi> that this particular perſon is the true Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> Firſt we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be certaine, abſolutely that the things required to the Election be performed: I'le inſtance in two things. Firſt, if the perſon be Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by thoſe who have no power to Elect, then the Election is Null, for if they had no power to Elect then they could confer no power nor priviledg on the perſon whom they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49882:29"/> do Elect, but 'tis uncertain whether the Election be performed by thoſe who have power to elect; for the right they have is either by divine or humane Law; but it is uncertain that they have a wright, either by divine or humane Law, pro. Firſt, it is uncertain that there is any right by divine Law, for let any man produce any divine Command or allowance; let them produce any proof that the authority of Electing the univerſal Biſhop who ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with the priviledges given to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> was beſtowed on the Cardinals. Secondly, the Election of the Pope was performed anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently by the ſuffrages of Clergy, and people, ſo <hi>Cornelius</hi> was choſen <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione Cleri &amp; plebis,</hi> ſaies <hi>Ciprian</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epist. l. 4. Epiſ. 2. 1.</note> and <hi>Gratian</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Distinct. 79. c. eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem.</note> quotes a ſaying of <hi>Anacletus,</hi> that God committed the Election <hi>bonis Sacerdotibus, &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus populis,</hi> to good Prieſts and Spiritual people. The like we have from <hi>Onuphrius*</hi> that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annot. in</hi> Plat. <hi>vita</hi> Pelag. 2.</note> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, <hi>more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49882:29"/> majorum</hi> was <hi>a Clero: S. P. Q. R.</hi> by the Clergy <hi>Senate,</hi> and people of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now then if the Election by the Cardinals was <hi>Jure divino</hi> then the former way of election was Null, and there was no true Pope till <hi>Celeſtin</hi> the ſecond, <hi>qui primus ſine ullo populi interventu Papa creatus eſt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Onuph. <hi>annot. in</hi> Plat. <hi>vita innocent.</hi> 2.</note> who was the firſt that was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pope without the peoples med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Election. Secondly, it is uncertain that there is any right by humane Law, for then it muſt pear that a right was conferred on them by the conſent of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, that they were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Proctors</hi> for the Univerſal Church, to chooſe on their behalf the Univerſal Paſtor; but if none of this appeares, nay, nor certainly that they are the rightfull Electors of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> barely <hi>quà</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> then it is not certain that the Pope is truly Elected, and therefore it cannot be <hi>de fide</hi> that this <hi>Clement</hi> the 9th is the ſucceſſor of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> Secondly, if the Pope
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49882:30"/> be elected for feare or profit, <hi>viz.</hi> if either the electors are compelled by Violence, or by bribes induced to elect one, if they be either over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awd with power or corrupted with gifts, then the election is null: Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Distinct. 79. c. ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis pecn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> determines, he ſhall be accounted <hi>Apoſtaticus non apoſtaticus;</hi> and the Councels of <hi>Lateran</hi> under <hi>Iulius</hi> ſecond declares that election to be null, and that by that election no power either in things temporall or ſperituall ſhall be allowed to the perſon elected; but now if he look into the ſtoryes of former elections, and the Myſteries of the <hi>Conclave</hi> at this day, he'le ſee, that it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to us whether the Pope be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elected: you may read the election of <hi>Formoſus</hi> the firſt <hi>Largitione Potius quam Virtute Aſſumitur ad Pontifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Platina <hi>in vita for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt.</hi>
               </note> for his gifts rather then Vertue of <hi>Steph,</hi> the ſixth of <hi>Sergius</hi> the third of <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleventh raiſed by the Authority and indeavours of his Mother <hi>Marocia,</hi> ſayes <hi>Onuphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Annot. in <hi>Plat.</hi> in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>John. 11th.</hi>
               </note>; <hi>Iohn</hi> thirteenth ſeized on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49882:30"/> Popedome by the power of his father <hi>Albericus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plat. <hi>in</hi> John 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </note>: <hi>Iohn</hi> the eighteenth got the Popedome by the power of <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> whom it was ſuppoſed he had bribed <note n="*" place="margin">Plat. <hi>in</hi> John 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </note>: <hi>Silveſter</hi> the ſecond obtayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Symonically firſt the Archbiſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Rhemes</hi> then of <hi>Ravenna, laſtly</hi> the Popedome, <hi>Majore Conatu diabolo adjuvante:</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plat. <hi>in</hi> Sylveſt. 2.</note>: <hi>Clement</hi> the ſecond by the Emperors Compulſion, <hi>Damaſus</hi> the ſecond by plaine force without any Conſent of the clergy or people enters on the Popedome yea it even became a Cuſtome, that every Ambitious perſon might ſeize on Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chayre, as <hi>Platina</hi> Complains <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>in: vita</hi> Clem. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> Damaſ. 2.</note>. What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeventeenth who came in like a fox, and left nothing untried by bribing and cheating that he might obtaine the Popedome? or of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth who was repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have Attained that dignity by the Ambition, and coveteouſneſs of ſome corrupt Prelates <note n="*" place="margin">Onuph. II <hi>in vita</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. 6.</note>? and how can we be abſolutely certain that this is a true pope, when wee find
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49882:31"/> the Eſſentialls of a true Election may be wanting? oft times the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were not free, either the Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors were over-awed, or their votes bought: and can we believe it is yet better? It is <hi>Platina's</hi> wiſh (when he ſaw how men were prefer'd to the Papacy, not for their piety, but for their gifts) <hi>Quem morem utinam ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando non retinuiſſent noſtra tempora;</hi> but he rather feares unleſſe God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, that the elections would be worſe, <hi>ſed hoc parum eſt pejora (ni deus caveat) aliquando viſuri ſumus:</hi> although the doores of the <hi>Conclave</hi> are kept ſhut, yet enough flyes abroad to ſhew the <hi>factions ſidings,</hi> and <hi>Pollicies</hi> within, how the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls are devided by their <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and <hi>dependencies</hi> on Princes; how ſome are <hi>frighted,</hi> others <hi>corrupted;</hi> ſome out of <hi>feare,</hi> others out of <hi>hatred</hi> &amp;c. giving their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>otes</hi> this way, or that way, and what certainty can wee have this is a true Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> lawful ſucceſſor to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> when we ſee ſo much ground to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49882:31"/> that the Eſſentials of a true election are oft times wanting but if any reply, that Gods providence will not permit any to paſs for Pope, who is not Pope; and that if the Church doe ſubmit to him as <hi>Pope,</hi> it is certain that he is Pope, and pro. we may ſtil believe that it is <hi>de fide</hi> that this <hi>Pope</hi> is lawful elected <hi>Pope.</hi> But this is ſaying without proving, much confidence with little reaſon: I therefore add, that there have been thoſe who paſſed for Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> and have been owned not only by their owne partyes, as in a <hi>Schiſme,</hi> but generally have paſſed for the true Pope, when yet their Elections were null; I ſay, have been generally owned, their names reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the catalogue, their decrees allowed, and yet the <hi>Eſſentialls</hi> requiſite to a right election are ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledged by their owne <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> to be wanting. Inſtance in <hi>Vigilius</hi> the firſt who ſuborned witneſſes aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt <hi>Silverius,</hi> that he would betray the Citty to the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and having
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49882:32"/> got him depoſed, was during the life of <hi>Silverius</hi> put into the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, and did (as <hi>Onuphrius</hi> confeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annot. in</hi> Plat. <hi>in Vita</hi> vigil. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Occupare per vim pontificatum Romanum;</hi> and yet this man is owned for Pope, without the leaſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any new election after the death of <hi>Sylverius,</hi> or any approbation and allowance from the clergy, and people by which he might lawfully enjoy that title. Again I inſtance in <hi>Benedict</hi> the fifth created <hi>Pope</hi> in a <hi>ſedition</hi> by the friends and dependents of <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteenth againſt <hi>Leo</hi> the eighth and yet he is both reckoned in the catalogue of <hi>Popes,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Onuph. <hi>Annot. in vita</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. 5.</note> and the ſucceeding <hi>Popes</hi> who aſſumed that name in reckoning of themſelves did allow him to be <hi>Pope;</hi> ſo in <hi>Iohn</hi> eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth though he came not in by the door, but during the life of <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifth ſeized on the Popedome, yet he is reckoned in the Catalogue of <hi>Popes</hi> which <hi>Platina</hi> admires <note n="*" place="margin">Plat. <hi>in vita</hi> John 18.</note>. When we thus ſee ſome owned for Popes who have never been duly elected,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49882:32"/> and do know how much tirannical compulſion may force an outward compliance, we cannot judge the ſubmiſſion and ſilence of the Church (as <hi>Suarez</hi> holds) Can be any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ground that the election was lawful. The ſum of this argument is this, if it be uncertain whether the <hi>eſſentialls</hi> of a juſt and true election be performed, then it is vncertain whether this be a true Pope and <hi>ex conſequenti</hi> it cannot be <hi>de fide</hi> that this Pope is the true ſuceſſor of Saint <hi>Peter. ſecondly</hi> we cannot be certain abſolutely that the things eſſentially required in the conſecration of the Pope are duly performed; I do not mean of ſuch things in the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which are only required by the cannon; but I ſpeak of thoſe things which they account eſſential, that there can be no conſecration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. <hi>firſt</hi> I inſtance in the <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> of the perſon to be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated: without baptiſme there is no ordination and <hi>pro.</hi> who have not been baptized cannot be ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49882:33"/> nor conſecrated, and are <hi>jure divino</hi> uncapable of orders, but we cannot be abſolutly certain that this perſon hath been baptized <hi>pro.</hi> we cannot be abſolutly certain that ſome thing eſſential to his conſecration is not wanting. <hi>Secondly</hi> In the <hi>intention</hi> of the conſecrators, for that is eſſentially neceſſary in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of orders by the Councells of <hi>Florence</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Decret. de Sacram.</note> and the council of <hi>Trent</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ. de Sacram. Can.</hi> 2.</note> requires an intention of doing, that which the Church doth, but it may fall out, that the conſecrators have no intention of doing any ſuch things either through negligence, or malice either they may intend to do noth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not to do that which the church doth <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to conſecrate: or they may intend to do this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act in ſport or merriment, or if then they cannot be certain that there is either an actuall or virtuall intention in the conſecrators, then they cannot be certain abſolutly that the eſſentialls of conſecration are duly performed.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49882:33"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Without <hi>intention</hi> in the perſon to be conſecrated, there is no true conſecration; ſo <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>third determines</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">C. majore: Extra. de Baptiſms.</note>; and <hi>Suarez</hi> call's it the common opinion of Divines that to the value of a ſacrament is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>intentio ſuſcipientis;</hi> but no man can be abſolutly certain, that the <hi>Pope</hi> either in any moment foregoing or during the act of conſecration, did any way intend to receive it; for ti's not the bare outward performing or doing, or receving which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: but the intending in the mind to do, or receive, and of that inward intention in the mind we cannot be certain. Many more things might be added concerning the conſecrators whether they were <hi>baptized?</hi> whether they were <hi>Prieſts?</hi> whether there is no <hi>defect</hi> in any thing eſſentially required to their baptiſme, or ordination? whether the intention in the conſecration was directed to that preſent perſon? for that <hi>Filliucius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſ. Conſc. tract.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 79.</note> requires now in theſe things ſince ti's Poſſible ſome eſſential
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49882:34"/> may be wanting, it follows no man can be certain abſolutly that this is the true <hi>Pope,</hi> and if he cannot be ſo abſolutly certain that this is the true <hi>Pope:</hi> becauſe ti's poſſible ſome eſſential has been wanting, then he cannot own it to be ſo <hi>de fide,</hi> nor ſwear that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches becauſe of its Union with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I inſtance in the Article of <hi>Trauſubſtantiation</hi> according to the Creed of <hi>Pius</hi> 4th, they ſwear <hi>that in the moſt holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt there is truly, really, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially the body, and blood, with the Soul, and Deity, of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and there is a converſion of the whole ſubſtance of bread into the body, and of the whole ſubſtance of wine into the blood,</hi> which Converſion the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church calls Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; and in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> there is an <hi>Anathema</hi> pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who ſhall deny that won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, and ſingular converſion of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49882:34"/> the whole ſubſtance of the bread into the body, and of the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the wine into the blood, the <hi>Species</hi> of bread, and wine onely remaining, which Converſion the Catholick Church moſt fitly calls Tranſubſtantiation: now though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Letter the Decree ſeems plain, and they will all cry up this wonderfull miracle, this <hi>Auguſt</hi> miſtery, yet in the explication of it and of the grounds whereupon they believe it they are perplexed; For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> although they pretend to derive this Doctrine from Scripture, yet it is not certain that there is any place of Scripture which neceſſarily infers this doctrine: ſo <hi>Scotus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>lib. ſent. dist.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3.</note> ſaies, and how the body of Chriſt is there, whether by Converſion of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into it, or without Converſion the ſubſtance, and accidents of bread remaining, <hi>non invenitur in Canone Bibliae</hi> ſaies <hi>Gabriel Biel</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne miſſ. lect.</hi> 40.</note>, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they uſually inſiſt on the 6th of St. <hi>John</hi> and the words of Inſtitution, this is my body, yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49882:35"/> others of great note among them, conclude that it is not expreſt in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, ſo <hi>Canus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Loc. Com. l. 3. c. 3. fund. 2.</note> holds, and <hi>Caje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane</hi> maintains † the 6th of St. <hi>John</hi> no way pertains to a Sacramental <note place="margin">*In 3. part. q. 80. art. vet.</note> eating; the ſame is held by <hi>Janſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Tapperus</hi> and others, cited by <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> and firſt ſome of them confeſs, they ſhould not have believed it, unleſs the Church had declared it to be <hi>de fide,</hi> for the Church by the ſpirit of truth did explain thoſe things which were obſcure in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Canus Loc. Com. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>fundam.</hi> 2.</note>; but then it would be ſtill in vain to endeavour to prove this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion from Scripture, becauſe there is no argument from thence which can ſufficiently convince: and to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue with us from thoſe Texts, which they think are not ſufficiently cogent without their Churches explanation, is altogether impertinent, for we are as uncertain of the infallibility of their Church in explaining thoſe Texts, as we are whether thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines be contained there, 'tis firſt as to us uncertain whether this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49882:35"/> Doctrine be delivered in Scripture. <hi>Secondly,</hi> though they affirm that by the words of inſtitution the bread is turned into the body, and the wine into the blood, yet they are perplexed about the meaning of them. <hi>Firſt,</hi> As whether there be any <hi>figure</hi> in the words or no? For if they be conſtrued figuratively, then they cannot certainly infer any tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; and firſt ſometimes they tell us there is no <hi>figure,</hi> or <hi>trope:</hi> yea, there ought to be none in the words of Inſtitution; but then how can the <hi>Cup</hi> be the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> there the Cup muſt be put for <hi>Wine</hi> in the Cup. Again, How can the Cup be the New Teſtament properly? For a Teſtament is the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators diſpoſition of his Eſtate; but the Wine in the Cup, or the thing contained under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> cannot be ſo in any proper ſenſe. Again, 'tis uncertain how the <hi>blood</hi> in the Cup can properly be called the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in his blood?</hi> for the blood is a <hi>phyſical,</hi> a Teſtament is a <hi>moral</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49882:36"/> thing: yea 'tis uncertain whether <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s * Explanation of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>de Eucharist. c.</hi> 11.</note> words be ſenſe; <hi>This blood under the ſpecies, is the New Teſtament under his blood:</hi> ſo that 'tis doubtful when they have done all they can, whether they can explain theſe words without a <hi>figure. Secondly,</hi> They are perplexed about the meaning of theſe words, as what is meant by <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum;</hi> for if they cannot reſolve what is meant by this <hi>Pronoun hoc,</hi> then they cannot determine what is the full meaning of this <hi>Propoſition;</hi> indeed <hi>Bellarmin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>de Euchar. c.</hi> 10.</note> tels us, <hi>Vera eſt Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum ſententia, qui volunt illud [Hoc] non demonſtrare panem, ſed rem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentam ſub ſpeciebus panis,</hi> &amp;c. That the opinion of Catholicks was true, who ſay, this Pronoun <hi>Hoc</hi> doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate not the Bread, but a thing contained under it; which although it was Bread before, yet it is now the Body of Chriſt: But he that conſults the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Writers, will find that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> only hides their quarrels, and obtrudes his own opinion for a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49882:36"/> general Doctrine. <hi>Johannes de Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Controv.</hi> 5. <hi>de Sacr. Euchar. Art.</hi> 4.</note> acknowledges the perplexity of their Doctors; ſome ſay the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noun <hi>Hoc</hi> demonſtrates the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of bread, becauſe the Pronoun muſt ſignifie a <hi>ſenſible</hi> thing, which exiſts when the deſignation is made, and remains when the ſignification of the word is finiſhed, but there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Sacrament which is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible when the words began to be pronounced, and when they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded beſides the <hi>accidents,</hi> firſt it muſt ſignifie the <hi>Accidents.</hi> Some ſay that this Pronoun demonſtrates the body of Chriſt as it is in it ſelf, or intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body of Chriſt in Heaven, which when the words are ſpoken begin to be in the <hi>Hoſt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Occam <hi>quod lib. vet. q.</hi> 2.</note>; and ſo the words ſignifie, <hi>this body is my body.</hi> Some ſay, it deſigns the ſubſtance of bread under thoſe accidents, and ſo the ſenſe is, <hi>The bread paſſes into the body of Chriſt; hoc eſt</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Art</hi> 1. <hi>in</hi> 2. <hi>part. dist.</hi> 8. <hi>lib.</hi> 4.</note>, <hi>ad hujus verbi prolationem hoc totum tranſire in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus.</hi> Some ſay, <hi>it deſigns ſomething common to the ſubſtance of bread, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49882:37"/> the Body of Chriſt under this reaſon of being contained under the ſpecies,</hi> and ſo the ſenſe ſhould be <hi>hoc quod ſub his acccidentibus continetur eſt corpus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> that which is contained under theſe accidents is my body, and this he pretends both <hi>Thomas,</hi> and <hi>Scotus</hi> holds. But ſtill the perplexity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, what that is which is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under theſe <hi>accidents,</hi> when they firſt ſay <hi>Hoc<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> for 'tis not the <hi>body</hi> till the words are ended. If it were the <hi>bread,</hi> then the <hi>Propoſition</hi> is true, <hi>this bread is my body;</hi> and that they will not g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant. Again, the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the Propoſition muſt have a diſtinct ſenſe; when firſt our Saviour took the bread into his hand, and ſaid <hi>this is,</hi> there muſt be ſome meaning of that part of the Propoſition, that Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive pronoun <hi>[Hoc]</hi> muſt refer to ſome thing preſent <note n="*" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Sacr. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. c.</hi> 11. § <hi>h. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c expl.</hi>
               </note>, and that which is evident to the <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehended by the <hi>imagination;</hi> what can that be but only <hi>bread?</hi> which they confeſs was exiſting du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpeaking of the words?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49882:37"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> they are perplexed, whether this Tranſubſtantiation be wrought by the Prayer of Conſecration, or the words of Inſtitution: that it was wrought by the Prayer, as well as the words was the opinion of ſome; that the Conſecration was the ſame with the bleſſing, and giving of thanks was the opinion of <hi>Thomas Durand, Hugo Cardinalis,</hi> &amp;c. yet ſtill how this can be is wholly intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and perplexed; for if our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Conſecrated by bleſſing, and giving of thanks, then he conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Prayer: but that they will not ſay, for they now conclude he Conſecrated by thoſe words, <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> as it is determined by the Council of <hi>Florence</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conc. <hi>Flor.</hi> in Instruct. Armen.</note>, that our Saviours words by which he made the <hi>Sacrament</hi> are the <hi>form</hi> of it, and that by the virtue of thoſe words the Conſecration is wrought, and ſo it is explained in the <hi>Roman</hi> Catechiſme: <hi>We are taught</hi> (ſaies the Catechiſme) <hi>by the Evangeliſt's Mathew, and Luke, and by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49882:38"/> this is the form of the Sacrament of the Euchariſt; hoc eſt corpus meum:</hi> well, but ſtill they are perplexed in what ſenſe the Prieſt uſes theſe words; for ſome think they are only repeated <hi>Hiſtorically</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Salmero <hi>tract.</hi> 13. <hi>tom.</hi> 9. Soto <hi>Art</hi> 5. <hi>q. 1. dist.</hi> 11.</note>; but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work this change, for ſo they only ſhew what was done by our Saviour in the firſt celebration of the Sacrament; others ſay, that they are ſpoken <hi>ſignificatively, (i. e.)</hi> that the Prieſt ſpeaking in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt ſignifies the turning of that bread into the body, ſo ſaies the <hi>Florentine</hi> Council, <hi>Sacerdos lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens in perſona Chriſti hoc conficit Sacramentum;</hi> but this will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Canon of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> where they are repeated Hiſtorical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for after the Prayer <hi>that God would make that offering to be to us the body, and blood of his Son Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 'tis immediately added in imitation of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> recital of the Story, <hi>who, the day before he ſuffered tooke bread into his holy and venerable hands, and lifting up his eyes unto
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49882:38"/> Heaven to thee his Father, God All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, gave thanks, he bleſſed, brake, and gave to his Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaying, take, eate, all of this, for this is my body:</hi> now what <hi>connexion</hi> can there be betwixt theſe latter words, and the former? unleſs they be. joyned as part of the Hiſtory: or what ſenſe in the former words <hi>he brake and gave to his Diſciples, ſaying, take eate all of this?</hi> if they break off ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly the repeating of the Story, and do not add theſe words, <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> Thus they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed on either hand, and firſt to avoid this intricacy they have diviſed a new way, that theſe words ſhould both be taken <hi>recita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè,</hi> and <hi>ſignificativè:</hi> both as part of the Story, and as the Prieſts words in the perſon of Chriſt by virtue of them turning the bread; but ſtill how can this be, that the ſame words ſhould be both a repetition of a former Story, and the production of the like effect? how is this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible that the ſame word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49882:39"/> any variation ſhould be uſed for theſe different purpoſes? both to relate what was done, and to work the ſame thing over again: and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of the blood 'tis added <hi>qui pro vohis &amp; pro multis effundetur in remiſſionem peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Canon miſſ. in miſſali</hi> Rom. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. 1631.</note>, which ſhall be ſhed for you, and for many for the remiſſion of ſins, now if theſe words be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>ſignificatively,</hi> then they are utterly falſe, as <hi>Durand</hi> argued, becauſe the body of Chriſt muſt ſuffer no more, nor the blood be ſhed: thus whether theſe words ſhall be taken <hi>narratively,</hi> or <hi>ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catively,</hi> or <hi>joyntly</hi> their <hi>Doctors</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree; and are wholly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed to ſolve the difficulties, and yet maintain their Ground. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> they are perplexed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this converſion be <hi>productive</hi> or <hi>adductive</hi> or <hi>Conſervative;</hi> and ſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> acknowledges, that though they agree there is a tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation <hi>(i. e.)</hi> converſion of the bread into the body, and of the wine into
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49882:39"/> the blood for the authority of the Councils and Church; yet in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of explaining it they differ, for they find ſo many difficulties in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the manner of this converſion, that though they maintain the decree in the termes of it yet they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed to find the ſenſe, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> they profeſſe to believe tranſubſtantiation but when they come to tell us what they mean by it, they then confeſſe they believe they know not what. For <hi>firſt,</hi> If this converſion be <hi>produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> then the body of Chriſt ſhould be made by theſe words, <hi>hoc eſt eorpus meum,</hi> but that which already hath it's being, cannot by that act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion receive it's being, for it is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have its being before that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Again, <hi>Every new reall action muſt have a new reall terme but there can be here no new reall terme, becauſe the terme was praeexiſting</hi> as <hi>Io. de Rhada</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>lib. ſent. Con.</hi> 7. <hi>Art.</hi> 2. <hi>Concl.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>argues;</hi> again <hi>Albertinus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coroll. tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>dub.</hi> 3. <hi>concl. vins.</hi> § 13.</note> urges this argument, <hi>if the word doth produce the body, then the body of Chriſt did concurre as an inſtrument
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49882:40"/> to the production of it ſelfe: but that is a contradiction, that the body ſhould be made ſubſtantially by it ſelf, for then it ſhould be both before and after it ſelf; before it ſelf, for it is preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to that Action by which it ſhould be produced after it ſelf as it is made by that Action, and by this means the ſame thing would be both effect and cauſe in the ſame kind, (i. e.) the body of Chriſt would be the cauſe of the Action by which it was produced, and that Action is the cauſality or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by which the body is produced.</hi> This way of Converſion <hi>productive</hi> they now diſlike, though it moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the Letter of the Canons, for they ſay, the bread is ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially turned into the body of Chriſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> Rom. <hi>ſub</hi> Nicol. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> Greg. 7.</note>: they compare this to the turning of water into Wine, but the Wine was produced in that miracle: they have been uſed to ſay, the Prieſt in the Sacrament creates his Creator; yea Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> Council makes this his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt doing Homage to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49882:40"/> 
               <hi>Laity</hi> for <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> honours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was <hi>nimis execrabile, manus quae in tantam eminentiam excreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint ut Deum cuncta creantem ſuo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterio creent,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, that thoſe hands which are advanced to that honour to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate God who created all things ſhould be the Servants of thoſe hands which are daily defiled with obſcene infection: this way of production though it was not defined, yet was thus publiquely pleaded by a Pope in Council but is now rejected. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> If this Converſion be <hi>conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative,</hi> then it will be wholly unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, for conſervation is the continuance of creation, or a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of that which already hath its being: either firſt they meant, that by the words of Conſecration was wrought a Conſervation of the body of Chriſt which was in heaven, or a conſervation of it under the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <hi>ſpecies:</hi> it cannot be meant that there is wrought a conſervation of it under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> unleſs there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49882:41"/> had been firſt an <hi>action creandi,</hi> for <hi>it cannot be thought that a thing is conſerved there where it is not ſuppoſed firſt to exiſt; but according to them, before theſe words the body did not exiſt there, ſo it could not be conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there: nor can it be meant of a conſervation of the body in Heaven, for conſervation is the continuance of an Action, but here is a new Action, and a new dependence wrought by the force of the words of conſecration,</hi> as <hi>Albertinus</hi> argues <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Corol.</hi> 3. <hi>dub.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 7.</note>. This pretence of conſervation hath few maintainers, firſt let us conſider the third way which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls <hi>communiorem &amp; tutiorem viam,</hi> the more common, and ſafe way of <hi>Thomas,</hi> and other grave Divines, I mean <hi>adductive</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> by the words the body of Chriſt is not made to exiſt ſimply, but to exiſt under thoſe <hi>ſpecies;</hi> that the bread ceaſes to be under thoſe <hi>accidents,</hi> and the body begins to be under them: that the body ſucceeds to exiſt under thoſe accidents not by having a new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49882:41"/> but only a new preſence: but here they are all together perplexed; for if it ſucceed here, where the bread was, it muſt either change place, or be produced, as <hi>Thomas</hi> inſtances in fire, <hi>if it begin to be in the Houſe, where it was not before, either it muſt be brought in hither, or be generated here,</hi> that it doth not change places is plain, for then it ſhould leave Heaven, when it was adduced un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecies of bread on Earth: if they ſay it muſt be produced here, how can that be? how can it be produced and not have its being produced? or how can it be ſaid that the ſubſtance of bread is turned into the ſubſtance of the body, when no new ſubſtance is made, but only the ſubſtance exiſts in a different <hi>ubi?</hi> or that one ſubſtance paſſes into another, when the one onely ſucceeds the other? <hi>or how ſhould it be the moſt perfect manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion as Bellarmine ſaies, when there is no change in the Nature of the body but only it is vailed under other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49882:42"/> accidents?</hi> when there is no new ſubſtance but only a new <hi>preſence?</hi> yea <hi>Rhada</hi> ſaies out of <hi>Scotus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 4. <hi>Cont.</hi> 6. <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>Concl.</hi> 3.</note>, <hi>there is no proper change at all? or how can it be moſt fitly cal'd Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea properly, and conveniently</hi> (as the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaies) <hi>when this converſion of the whole ſubſtance of bread into the whole ſubſtance of the body is no more then that the one exiſted where the other did? and the term [ad quem] of this converſion is not any ſubſtance but an accidenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis modus, a preſence where it was not before?</hi> There are ſome other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, wherewith they labour to ſolve theſe perplexities, but what one thinks that he builds, another ſoon pulls down, and there be ſo many contrary opinions in ſtating this converſion, that 'tis eaſy to ſee, they could not ſatisfie others, who are ſo wholly unſatisfied themſelves: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> there are ſo many <hi>intrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> about the <hi>ſpecies</hi> themſelves, <hi>where</hi> they are ſubjected; what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> betwixt the body of Chriſt and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49882:42"/> thoſe accidents, whether this body be an <hi>Organical</hi> body or no? when it <hi>ceaſes</hi> to be under the ſpecies, if there be no <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of bread what then is broken? what <hi>chewed?</hi> what <hi>digeſted?</hi> what is it which <hi>nouriſhes?</hi> what is it which <hi>breeds worms,</hi> &amp;c? there are ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricacies, that thoſe who ſtifly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this Doctrine of Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, know not how to winde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out: I inſtance in ſome few things. <hi>Firſt, what is it that is broken?</hi> either the body or the ſpecies: it cannot be the body, for the body cannot be divided into parts; and firſt, to ſay that the body is broken, and chewed by the teeth, unleſs they be underſtood in a ſound ſenſe, <hi>in majorem incides hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſin quam ipſe habuit Berengarius,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Gloſs</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gloſs. in Can. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reng.</hi> de Conſecr. dist. 2.</note>, and yet in theſe words <hi>Berengarius</hi> was forced to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cant, <hi>panem &amp; vinum non ſolum eſſe Sacramentum, ſed verum corpus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; in veritate manibus Sacerdotum frangi, fidelium dentibus atteri</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Can. <hi>ego</hi> Bereng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ibi.</hi>
               </note>, that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49882:43"/> the body was in truth held in the Prieſt hands, broken, and chewed with the teeth: which words ſaies <hi>Serenus Creſſy,</hi> are far from being juſtifiable, unleſs they be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Sacramentally (i. e.)</hi> for the outward ſpecies, which yet he ſees cannot be, for it's ſaid <hi>not only is a Sacrament, but the body, &amp;c. and is in truth held in the Prieſts hand, broken and chewed,</hi> and if it be ſo, then Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> and the Council erred which preſcribed this <hi>recantation,</hi> and how will he ſwallow that? it cannot be the ſpecies, for no man can break or chew colour, or ſavour, or figure, &amp;c. but only ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Secondly,</hi> what is it that nouriſhes? it is either the body or the ſpecies. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it cannot be the body; for the body of Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be turned into our bodies, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Chriſts body could not be whole, for thouſands of men muſt have part of his body; <hi>It is nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us</hi> (ſaies <hi>Creſſy) but not after a Carnall manner;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut how can this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49882:43"/> be? for if it be not nouriſhment after a Carnal manner, then it muſt be after a <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and how can our bodies be nouriſhed Spiritually? <hi>If there be nouriſhment, there muſt be ſomething digeſted, but Chriſts body is not turned into our bodies by digeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſaies he: <hi>If there be nouriſhment, then ſomething muſt be added to our bodies but Chriſts body is not added to our bodies:</hi> Let him firſt either ſhew how bodies can be nouriſhed Spiritually, or confeſs that he ſpeaks, what he doth not underſtand. Some firſt among them ſay, <hi>The body ceaſes to be under the ſpecies when it comes into the belly,</hi> others ſay, <hi>while it is in the mouth;</hi> others, <hi>that while the ſpecies remains the body remains;</hi> and firſt while the ſpecies are in the belly, the body of Chriſt is there <note n="*" place="margin">Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood <hi>in Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. prov. de ſum. trin. c. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſ. p. glutiant.</hi>
               </note>, but the <hi>Gloſs</hi> on the Canon <hi>non iſte de conſecrat. diſtinct.</hi> 2. ſaies, the body doth not come down into the belly, <hi>quouſque verò pergulam procedat neſcio;</hi> how far it goeth into the Throat I know not; yet
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49882:44"/> he concludeth, <hi>'tis not digeſted as other meats are, nor paſſes into the nouriſhment of the body, for it is the food of the Soul, and not of the body:</hi> Well, can it be the ſpecies? Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that alſo is uncertain for nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing is the reparation of a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, not of accidents, and firſt muſt be by a ſubſtance, and not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by accidents: in nouriſhing the food muſt be tranſmuted into the body, and how can accidents be ſo? to ſalve all this, God muſt afford ſome matter, either reſtore the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer matter of bread, or produce ſome new matter, or which is moſt miraculous to me, <hi>all this muſt be done without a miracle ſaies Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. 3. <hi>de Euchar. c.</hi> 24. <hi>reſp. ad arg.</hi> 6.</note>; <hi>for the Naturall Order of things require it, (i. e.) when the diſpoſitions requiſite for introducing the form are made, after the previous alteration of the ſpecies, then the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of things requiring it, God muſt ſubſtitute matter:</hi> but what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hath <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that all theſe things ſhall be as he fancies? that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49882:44"/> the accidents ſhall be diſpoſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out matter, in which they ſhould be ſubjected? that when theſe mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial diſpoſitions are perfected God will ſubſtitute matter: many ſuch things there are which will trouble him to reſolve. All this ſhews that this is a moſt perplexed Doctrine, for if the ſubſtance of bread be gone, what can nouriſh? it muſt either be the body or the ſpecies; and yet neither of theſe can they certainly fix on. Thirdly, what is it that is corrupted? as when worms are generated of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> it cannot be the body, <hi>for God will not ſuffer his holy one to ſee Corruption.</hi> If they ſay the ſpecies, neither can that be, for Corruption is properly of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, neither can the worms be generated of bare accidents, as of colour, figure, or the like, there muſt be then ſome new matter crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into which the form of worms muſt be introduced, and how ſtrange muſt this be? that men to free themſelves from theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49882:45"/> are forced to ſhelter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under pretence of multitude of miracles of which not one can be perceived by our ſenſes. <hi>Durand</hi> mentions <hi>eleven</hi> miracles in Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rationale div. offic. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note>, and yet there is not the leaſt appearance to our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that there is one; yea to clear themſelves from the perplexities which attend this Doctrine they are forced to fly to more, <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 75. <hi>art.</hi> 8. <hi>arg.</hi> 3.</note>, ſaies there are <hi>plura difficiliora,</hi> &amp;c. more difficulties than in the creation. And <hi>Scotus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>lib. ſentent. dist.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3.</note> objects to himſelf, that this one opinion is the occaſion of turning all Philoſophers, and thoſe that follow Natural rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the faith, for they would think, that there are greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies (ſuppoſing there be no ſubſtance of bread remaining) than in the article of the Incarnation, <hi>&amp; propter haec fidem patere contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui omnium ſequentium rationem;</hi> this expoſes Religion to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all that follow reaſon: for to believe that which ſeems ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49882:45"/> much both againſt ſenſe and reaſon, and ſo little appearance of revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to defend it, is ſtrange to wiſe, and rational men, who know not how to digeſt ſuch uncertain, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and abſur'd opinions, unleſs they can bring their faith to believe what they judge impoſſible. The ſum of this ſecond argument to prove the perplexities of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church in the Doctrines ſhe hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined is taken from the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, intricacies, and perplexities in the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I inſtance in the Doctrine of <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſs.</hi> 25. <hi>de Invoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi> &amp;c.</note> commands all who have any cure to teach this, <hi>That the Saints reigning with Chriſt offer up their Prayers for men to God: that it is good and profitable, humbly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them, and for the benefits to be obtained of God by his Son, who is our only Redeemer, and Saviour, to fly to their Prayers, help, and aid,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49882:46"/> and it declares, <hi>that all thoſe think impiouſly, who deny that the Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying Eternal happineſs are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked; or who aſſert that they do not pray for men; or that it is fooliſh to ſupplicate to them, either with the voice, or the mind:</hi> Now this Doctrine is ſo dubious, that it is unreaſonable to make it an article of faith. for firſt though the Saints ſhould pray for us, yet 'tis no neceſſary inference, firſt we muſt pray to them: no more then if a friend at an hundred miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhould every day pray for us, firſt we muſt every day ſay at that diſtance, <hi>ora pro nobis.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is no way certain that it is good, and profitable to fly to their Prayers, help, and aide, for if it be not certain that they know our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, it is not certain that it is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to fly to their prayers; now if they know them it muſt be either that they hear theſe themſelves, or are revealed to them by God, or diſcover'd to them by the holy <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> But firſt, it is not certain that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49882:46"/> they themſelves can heare them; for though according to <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat ſouls may intuitively ſee every vocal oration which they might have known if they were joyned to the body, and alſo mental ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and may behold the eſſence, and internal operation of our ſouls, yet all this muſt be underſtood <hi>niſi immoderata diſtantia impediat,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Io. de Rhada. <hi>Cont.</hi> 16. <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>Concl.</hi> 1.</note> vnleſs there be an immoderate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for no Agent can act but upon a patient duly approximated to it, and an immoderate diſtance hinders the approximation: firſt unleſs the Seperate Soul be in its due diſtance, it cannot underſtand theſe Prayers: and ſo <hi>Biel</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Canon Miſſa Lect.</hi> 31.</note> Sayes <hi>that they cannot know, that way, either mental or vocal Prayers by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the immoderate diſtance:</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing (I ſay) with <hi>Scotus,</hi> that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Souls may hear thoſe Prayers, which they might have known, when they were joyned to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: yet this is not certain how far this diſtance reaches; and what is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49882:47"/> the Sphear of their activity; and 'tis far leſs certain, whether the Saints in Heaven can at that diſtance hear the many ſuppliants in ſeveral parts of the Earth; and ſee thoſe ſecret deſires which never diſcover'd themſelves in words. Secondly, it is no way certain that the Prayers of men are diſcover'd by the Angels to the Saints, for it is not certain, that the Angels can know the thoughts <note n="*" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Sanct. Beatit. c.</hi> 20.</note>; or if they do, 'tis not certain that they do diſcover theſe things to them. 'Tis not certain they do know them, yea its moſt certain that God only knoweth them <note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 6. 30.</note>, and if they do know them, yet 'tis not certain that they are either bound by Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Office to repreſent theſe things to the Saints. Thirdly, the uſual way they pitch on is either Gods revelation to the Saints as he revealed things which were future to the Prophets: or elſe that the Saints ſee all things in God from the begining of their happineſs, which any way pertain to them: and this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49882:47"/> way <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls the more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable opinion, but neither of theſe waies is certain. For firſt, 'tis no way certain that God doth reveal theſe Prayers to the Saints, which are made to them. And if he ſhould as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> argues, the Church could not ſo confidently ſay to the Saints, <hi>Pray for us,</hi> as rather, <hi>Pray to God that he would reveal theſe Prayers to them;</hi> no man can ſay, that God is any way bound to reveal theſe things, or <hi>de facto</hi> that he doth ſo, and how then can we be certain that God will reveal theſe Prayers to them. Secondly, 'tis not certain that they ſee theſe things in the word, as in a Corporeal Glaſs men may ſee clearly and diſtinctly what appears, according to <hi>Becanus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Contr. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. §. 4.</note> his explication. For firſt, 'tis no way neceſſary to the Saints happineſs, that they ſhould ſee theſe things in God, neither from the nature of happineſs, becauſe as <hi>Scotus</hi> and his followers argue, <hi>the proper nature of Happineſs conſiſts in ſeeing God, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49882:48"/> his Attributes, but the Prayers of Saints are diſtinct from God, and his Attributes, firſt 'tis not neceſſary they ſhould ſee theſe, ex ratione beatitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhada Cont.</hi> 16. <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>Concl.</hi> 3.</note>; nor is it a conſequent flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their happineſs, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may ſee in his Eſſence thoſe things which flow from his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, firſt they may ſee the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made by the Creatures: though they may ſee his works about the Creature, I mean the <hi>Idea</hi> of his works which is himſelf, yet it doth not follow, they ſhould ſee what ever the Creature himſelf doth: and ſo <hi>Biel</hi> tells us <hi>that it is no part of their Eſſential beatitude, nor is it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that it pertains to their acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal beatitude</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Biel <hi>in Canon Miſſa Lect.</hi> 31.</note>. Secondly, as it is not neceſſary they ſhould, ſo it is not certain, that they do ſee all things in the Glaſs of the Divine Eſſence: for either then they ſee all things ſimply in that Glaſs, or only ſuch things as God is pleaſed to permit them to ſee; if all things ſimply, then they muſt needs know all future con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49882:48"/> they muſt know the day, and hour when the Son ſhall come to judge the world, and yet our Saviour ſaith, of that hour knoweth no man, no not the Angels, though they alwaies ſee the face of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who is in Heaven <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 18. 10.</note>: If they ſee ſuch things only as God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to diſcover to them, then we cannot be certain that they know our prayers, unleſs we are firſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that God will diſcover them to them: If this Glaſs they talke of diſcovers all things <hi>tanquam per na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalem communicationem,</hi> then they muſt ſee all future contingencies, if the Glaſs diſcovers things only <hi>tanquam per voluntariam communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem,</hi> then they know no more then he is pleaſed to communicate, and without his revelation we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be certain what that is, which he doth communicate: and if we cannot be certain they know our Prayers, we cannot be certain that it is profitable to fly to their Prayers. Thirdly, it is no way <hi>certain</hi> that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49882:49"/> they <hi>Pray</hi> for us, I confeſs it is not <hi>incredible</hi> that they Pray for their fellow members; none will deny that their Charity is more ardent in Heaven, then it was on Earth, and the greater their Charity is it will appear in more eminent effects (ſo far as their conditiou permits) to their Brethren. Thus far we do not queſtion whether they pray for us, I mean <hi>in genere</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Field <hi>of the Church l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>; yea, what if I ſhould add that it is not <hi>incredible,</hi> but that they pray for their friends and acquaintance? and in general deſire the removal of Evils, and the granting thoſe things which are neceſſary for their Salvation? yea, if I ſhould add further that it is not <hi>incredible,</hi> but that they pray for them whoſe Conditions on Earth they remember, even this alſo ſome eminent <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have thought <note n="†" place="margin">Andrews <hi>Opuſc. Posth. Reſp. ad c.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>Repl. Card.</hi> Perron Montac. <hi>adv.</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng. <hi>pag.</hi> 21.</note>: yet ſtill 'tis no way certain, not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain (I ſay) that they do pray in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular for their fellow members, or remember in their Prayers all the particular neceſſities of the faithfull
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49882:49"/> on earth: for if we ſay we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that they do thus particularly pray, the queſtion will return which way? or by what ground are we certainly aſſured? and it will apear there is no certain ground but only ſome gueſſes, and ſuppoſed probabilities, and ꝑo. this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine muſt be doubtful, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I inſtance in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> declares, <hi>That ſince there was a power of beſtowing Indulgences gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt to the Church, and the Church from the moſt ancient times hath uſed it: The Synod doth teach, that the uſe of them being very wholſome to Chriſtian people and approved by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Councils to be retained in the Church: and Anathematizes them who either ſay they are unprofitable, or deny the Churches power to beſtow them.</hi> The ſame alſo is ſworn by their Clergy in the profeſſion of faith made by <hi>Pius</hi> 4. <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiarum
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49882:50"/> Poteſtatem à Chriſto in Eccleſia relictam eſſe, illarúmque uſum Chriſtiano Populo maxime ſalutarem eſſe affirmo.</hi> No more was ſaid of this Article by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> whether for haſt of ending the Council: or rather for multiplicity of abſtruſe queſtions, which muſt have been determined as the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Council ſayes, I cannot judge. The meaning of the <hi>article</hi> muſt be gathered from the practice of their Church and opinion of their <hi>Doctors:</hi> tis certain in the practice of their Church that there are indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences granted by the <hi>Pope</hi> in which he doth abſolve <hi>à culpa et poena</hi> both from fault, and puniſhment. That for viſiting ſuch a <hi>Church</hi> frequenting ſuch a <hi>Station,</hi> Saying over at ſuch an <hi>Altar</hi> ſo many times <hi>Ave Maria</hi> or <hi>pater noſter,</hi> they ſhall have <hi>plenam remiſſionem peccatorum,</hi> ſo it is in the <hi>Bul</hi> of indulgence for celebrating the year of <hi>Jubilee;</hi> in the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Jubilees by <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8th. <note n="*" place="margin">Platina <hi>in vit</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac. 8.</note> he gave to thoſe who viſited
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49882:50"/> the threſholds of the Apoſtles <hi>plenam omnium peccatorum remiſſionem</hi> a full remiſſion of all ſins. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10th gave to thoſe who devoutly repeated this <hi>Prayer</hi> after the divine <hi>Office,</hi> (to the holy, and undivided <hi>Trinity,</hi> the <hi>humanity</hi> of Chriſt Crucified, the fruitful integrity of the moſt bleſſed <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin</hi> be eternal praiſe, glory, and honor) Indulgence of all the defects, and faults which in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the office were contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by humane frailty. <note n="*" place="margin">Gavant <hi>Theſ. Sacr. Rit. in. Fine Libri.</hi>
               </note> Nothing is more common in the Buls for the <hi>Cruſadoes</hi> then pardon for half ſins, or for all ſins, ſo in the Cruſado, which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 6th publiſht againſt the adherents of <hi>Clement</hi> there were given to <hi>Henry Spenſer</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich mirabiles indulgentiae,*</hi> by <note place="margin">† Hen. Knighton <hi>Cron. l.</hi> 5 <hi>inter ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pt. Hist.</hi> Anglic. <hi>Pag.</hi> 2671.</note> the authority of which he did ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve as well the dead as the living, for whom there was a ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution from all the fault and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: and ſome of his <hi>Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> affirmed, that at their command the Angels deſcended from Heaven,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49882:51"/> and took the ſouls which were in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> out of their puniſhment, and inſtantly carried them to Heaven. In the Cruſadoes againſt the <hi>Albigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Innocent</hi> promiſed to all, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died in the way or in battel, on Gods part and by the authority of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> abſolution from all the ſins contracted in their lives, which they had confeſt, and for which they had not done <hi>penance</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rigord. 1 ist. An. 1208 <hi>Pag.</hi> 207.</note>. Sometimes the indulgence runs for <hi>penance</hi> injoyned; ſo for repeating the new office of the <hi>Bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin</hi> if they be not obliged to do it, <hi>Tius</hi> 5 remits 50 days <hi>de poenitentiis injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis,</hi> as oft as they do it: for repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the office of the dead, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the 7 <hi>penitential</hi> pſalms, or the <hi>Graduals</hi> 40 days, and ſo the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence runs which <hi>Martin</hi> the 50 anno 1429 gave for the Celebration of <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day to all that were preſent at the <hi>Mattins</hi> and <hi>Evenſong</hi> of the feaſt 200 dayes indulgence, to all that were preſent at the <hi>Prime,</hi> the <hi>third,</hi> the <hi>ſixth,</hi> the <hi>ninth,</hi> or
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49882:51"/> the <hi>Completory</hi> of that feaſt 80 days, to the Prieſts who ſaid <hi>Maſs</hi> for every Maſs 100 days, to thoſe who follow the proceſſion in which the <hi>Hoſt</hi> is carried 100 days, &amp;c. to indure every year for ever, <note n="*" place="margin">Conſt. <hi>Prov. Tit de ſerlis gloſſ. In Cap. Ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cript. p. Corp. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti.</hi>
               </note> Sometimes they are Indulgences <hi>pro poenitentiis injungendis,</hi> for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of Penance which might be enjoyned, ſometimes the words run, <hi>Indulgentiam in Domino miſerecordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter relaxamus:</hi> and theſe Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are ſome for daies; ſo every Arch Biſhop and Biſhop at their firſt coming to their <hi>Cathedrals*</hi> grant <note place="margin">† <hi>Carem. Epſc. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 40 daies: ſometimes for one year as at the <hi>dedication</hi> of a Church, ſometimes for 7, ſometimes for an 100 years, ſometimes for 1000 So the Monaſtery of <hi>St. Sebaſtian in Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbis</hi> hath Indulgences of 3000 years for all that viſit a ſtone which hath the print of our Saviours foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps: by other Popes 7000 years were granted on the feaſt of the <hi>Aſoention</hi> unto the <hi>Calends</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> every day 4000 years on St <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49882:52"/> day 3000 years, and 40 days of Indulgence, and all theſe are doubled in <hi>Lent</hi> and in the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble feſtivals. I could reckon up multitudes of large Indulgences, which ſome bountiful Popes have beſtowed, as at <hi>Crowland</hi> Abby a pardon of 8000 years: ſo the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don procured by <hi>Thomas Cromwel*</hi> 
               <note place="margin">† <hi>Acts and Monum. in the life of</hi> Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel. <hi>Pag.</hi> 49.</note> for <hi>Boſton</hi> from <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond, that all who are of the gylde of our <hi>Lady</hi> in <hi>St. Botolphs</hi> Church in <hi>Boſton</hi> who reſort to the ſaid Chappel on the Nativity or Aſſumption of our <hi>Lady,</hi> giving to the ſupport of the Chappel at every ſuch feſtival, ſhall have full remiſſion of all his ſins: or if they could not come to that Chappel, yet if they ſaid at their Parriſh Church, one <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> they ſhould have like remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and thoſe that came every Fryday to that Chapel ſhould have as much remiſſion, as if they went to the Chappel cal'd <hi>Scala Coeli,</hi> &amp;c. Or if their Popes are ſparing, yet their Prieſts aſſure men of greater bounty
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49882:52"/> for ſaying a prayer which begins <hi>O Altiſſma Crux &amp;c</hi> they ſhall have as many years Indulgence as there is gravel in the ſea, or graſs on the ground. This is the practice of their Church, by which we may ſee the meaning of the <hi>Article</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of their Doctors reaches not ſo farr as the practice: for they tell us, Indulgence is the remiſſion of temporal puniſhment <note n="*" place="margin">Summa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. P. Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia.</note>, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of temporal puniſhment due by divine Judgment for actual ſins, through the application of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant ſatisfaction of Chriſt and the Saints, by him who hath power to diſpence it: this Doctrine of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences leans on 4 things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> that after the remiſſion of the fault and the eternal puniſhment, there is yet a temporal puniſhment due. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That a righteous man not onely ſatiſfies for himſelfe by his own merit, but may apply his own ſatisfaction to others. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That there is a treaſure in the Church made up of the ſuperabundant me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49882:53"/> and ſatisfaction of Chriſt, and the Saints. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That there is a power in the Church appointed by Chriſt to diſpenſe this Treaſure; or thus as others ſpeak, there are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhments left unremitted, though God pardon the eternal, that theſe puniſhments muſt be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied either in this life, or hereafter that the <hi>Penances</hi> impoſed by the Prieſts are ſatisfactions for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment they ſhould undergo, that a righteous perſon may by the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundance of his own <hi>Merit,</hi> ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy for that which ought to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by another, that there is a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thoſe ſuperabundant merits of Chriſt, and the Saints. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That there is a power to diſpenſe this Treaſure according as it ſhal ſeem fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Many things are neceſsary for the underſtanding of this Doctrine, and yet every thing in it perplexed and uncertain: I will inſtance in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The value of them, if there can be no certainty by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49882:53"/> that there is any profit by theſe Indulgences, then we have no reaſon to profeſſe this to be an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of faith, but there is no certainty of any benifit by them. For <hi>Firſt,</hi> If the Indulgences do <hi>valere quantum ſonat,</hi> are as much worth as the words ſound, then theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences ſhould remit the guilt of all ſin. For many Indulgences tell us of a <hi>remiſſio omnium peccatorum,</hi> of a remiſſion <hi>à culpa &amp; poena;</hi> and this Article <hi>per paſſiones Sanctorum Indulgentiis Communicatas non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè redimi peccata noſtra;</hi> that our ſins are not properly redeemed by the paſſions of Saints Communicated by Indulgences, was condemned by <hi>Leo</hi> 10. and <hi>Pius</hi> 5. but now that they do not remit any is the common opinion, yea and is certain <hi>de fide Suarez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Diſp. 50. Sect. 1.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Filliucius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cas. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcion tract. 8. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 7. n.</hi> 3180.</note> atteſt. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not certain that they remit any puniſhment, for the eternal is already pardoned and there needs no farther Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and as for the temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49882:54"/> which (they ſay) remains. <hi>Firſt,</hi> there are many temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments due to the ſinner, which are not taken away by the moſt plenary Indulgence. Suppoſe God ſhould inflict a diſeaſe for the ſatisfaction of the temporal puniſhments remaining unpayed, they will then tell us that this Indulgence doth not take away natural puniſhment which God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts for actual ſin, as the Plague which God brought upon the people for <hi>Davids</hi> ſin. <note n="*" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. l. 1. c. 7. l. 2. c. 7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> theſe Indulgences do not take away the puniſhment inflicted <hi>in foro externo</hi> whether Civil or Ecclefiaſtical, that's alſo granted by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. ibid, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> It it is not certain that they take away the puniſhments which may be injoyned by the ancient <hi>Canon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for as <hi>Cajetan</hi> argues, nothing can be taken away by the Indulgence, but what a man was bound to perform but the puniſhments which are not enjoyned by the Judge no man is bound to perform ꝑo. for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Canons are only taxed
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49882:54"/> to be enjoyned by the Judge, ꝑo. till they are actually enjoyned no man can be obliged to perform them. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is not certain that they take away all the puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the <hi>Confeſſor</hi> in the Court of Penance, for as <hi>Valentia</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tract. de Indulg. Punct. 3.</note> ſaies, <hi>the Confeſſor is bound for the integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Sacrament to injoyne, and the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitent to performe wholſom Penance,</hi> and if the Penitent is bound to perform thoſe ſatisfactions, then the Indulgence doth not take them away. Againe <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaies, <hi>this is the uſe of the Church that whoſoever intend to get any Indulgences, are wont to confeſs, and perform the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions injoyned,</hi> but then to what profit ſerves the Indulgence, if it frees them only from thoſe ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which they have already fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led? they tell us further, <hi>that we cannot be certain that we receive any benefit by the Indulgence, and</hi> ꝑo. <hi>for greater merit, and ſecurity, we ſhould perform the ſatisfactions injoyned; ob majus meritum &amp; ſecuritatem,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49882:55"/> neque enim poteſt quis eſſe certus de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia percepta</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Filliuc.</hi> Caſ. Conſc. Tract. 8. Part. 3. c. 7. u. 176.</note> and ſince no man can be certain that he receives any benefit by an Indulgence, ꝑo. no wonder if he muſt for his own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity indeavour to perform the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions impoſed, and if he is ſtill bound to endeavour to perform them by himſelf, then it is not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they take away the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment injoyned. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is not certain that they take away the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due by the Judgment of God. Suppoſe there be a puniſhment due here, or to be inflicted in <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> hereafter, yet there is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that theſe Indulgences take away this puniſhment. For, <hi>firſt,</hi> It is uncertain whether the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Keyes</hi> can extend further, than to take away that puniſhment, which it might inflict: but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Keyes reaches not to inflict theſe puniſhments: <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> It is no way certain whether the Indulgence be valuable further, then according to the worthineſs,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49882:55"/> and devotion of him who receives the Indulgence, and then 'tis no way certain that there is any benefit by the Indulgence: <hi>Angelus de Clava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Summa. Angelica. P. Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia.</note> tells us that <hi>quoad augmentum Gratiae &amp; Gloriae,</hi> they are onely ſo much worth as is the devotion of him that receives them, and no more: but in reſpect of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is to be inflicted in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, <hi>tantum dimittit quantum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> remitts what it expreſſes: but how comes the value of the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence for the gaining an augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Glory, to depend on the worth of the receiver, and not for gaining a freedome from paine? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Indulgence requires they ſhould be contrite, and have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly confeſſed their ſins, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this they gain no benefit by the Indulgence; but then what certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whether any benefit come from the Indulgence, or rather that it comes from the Contrition of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, which alſo would availe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Indulgence? others ꝑo. go
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49882:56"/> further, and tell us they are never ſo much worth as is promiſed, <hi>ſed aliquid valent modicum, ſecundum quod mereter fides &amp; devotio,</hi> ſo <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naventure</hi> ſaies <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>Dist.</hi> 21.</note> ſome held. Thus it is no way certain according to themſelves, what the real advantage is whether they bring any? and if it be no way certain, then we cannot be bound to profeſs this as an Article of our Faith, that Indulgences are wholeſome and profitable; Indeed I will allow them to be profitable, but 'tis to the Popes <hi>purſe,</hi> not to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents <hi>Soul:</hi> you may read the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage which Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 6. made by the Indulgence publiſht in <hi>England</hi> 1382. <hi>Henry Spenſer</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> gathered (ſaies <hi>Henry Knighton</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chron.</hi> Heary Knighton <hi>pag.</hi> 2671.</note>) an incredible ſum of Gold and Silver and Jewels and Rings and Diſhes and Spoons and other Ornaments, ſpecially from Ladies and other women: and that both men and women gave not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording, but even beyond their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, that their dead friends as well
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49882:56"/> as themſelves might receive the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of abſolution from their ſins, which none could obtain, unleſs they contributed according to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The matter of them, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> the <hi>Superfluous</hi> ſatisfactions of Chriſt and the Saints, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the <hi>Treaſure</hi> of the Church, for (ſay they) <hi>there can be no remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of puniſhments injoyned for ſins, unleſs there be ſome recompenſe made by ſome who have performed more then was due from them:</hi> but if it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether there be any ſuch Treaſure, then the Doctrine of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences is uncertain. <hi>Firſt,</hi> 'Tis not certain that there is any ſuch Treaſure of the Saints ſatisfactions reſerved in the Church; <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe 'tis not certain, that they have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered more then they have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though they ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer more then they have deſerved, yet 'tis is not certain, that they do or can ſuffer more then they are bound
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49882:57"/> in obedience to God. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis not certain, that if they do or ſuffer only, what they are bound in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, that they can ſatisfie by that obedience for another, for where they only pay that which is required of them there is nothing ſuperfluous, and ꝑo. nothing to be put into the Treaſure. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> 'Tis not certain, but their ſufferings are as much or more rewarded, then is due or can be due to them; and if they are fully rewarded, then they cannot diſcharge another mans debt: and upon this ground <hi>Franc. Mayro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and <hi>Angel. de Clavaſio</hi> deny the ſatisfactions of the Saints can be put into the Treaſure †. <note place="margin">* Sum. Angelica. <hi>P.</hi> Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia. N. 9:</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis not <hi>certain</hi> that there is any treaſure made up of the ſuperfluous ſatisfactions of Chriſt, and his Church. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> If the Treaſure of Chriſts ſatisfactions be infinite then it is not certain, that any thing can be added to it, for an infinite cannot be increaſed, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe there ſhould be an infinite grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49882:57"/> than an infinite. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not certain, that there is any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by thoſe ſatisfactions of the Saints, for if Chriſts merit be of an infinite value, then there is nothing that can be procured by the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Saints, which hath not been allready procured by Chriſts merit: nor is there any thing we can gaine by the ſatisfactions of Saints but we may much more receive it from the infinite merit of Chriſt. If then we have no certainty, that there is any uſe of this Treaſure, we can then have no certainty that there is any ſuch Treaſure. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is no way certain, that there is any ſuch Treaſure of the ſuperfluous ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions of Chriſt; becauſe, <hi>firſt,</hi> It is not certain, that any thing Chriſt did, or ſuffer'd, could be more than he was bound to undergo, as he became our <hi>Surety</hi> and in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the command of his Father was bound to do, or ſuffer, what ever his Father required for the full ſatisfaction of his <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and if his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49882:58"/> ſatisfactions were in this reſpect ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, then they cannot be call'd ſuperfluous. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though his ſatisfaction was infinite, yet it is not certain, that any thing was ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; becauſe all that a finite perſon can do or ſuffer, can never ſatisfie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Juſtice. And it is not certain, when the offender deſerves the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt puiſhment both here, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after which he is capable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, that every work or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (though of an infinite perſon) can be ſufficiently ſatisfactory to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate that debt. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though his ſatisfaction was ſufficient for more, then it was actually extended to, yet 'tis no more certain, ꝑo. ſome ſatisfactions are ſuperfluous, than that the light of the <hi>Sun</hi> (which would enlighten thouſands more, than actually receive benefit by it) is ſo: or that Gods <hi>Omnipotency</hi> is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, becauſe it may create more worlds, than already are. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This Doctrine contains many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, and inſoluble ſcruples, as,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49882:58"/> which are neceſſary and which ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions are ſuperfluous? what part of Chriſts ſatisfactions are rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? and what not? for thoſe which are allready rewarded cannot be put into the common ſtock; whether the ſame merit, which merited Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for himſelf? or that which meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the pardon of Eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? or that there is ſome other merit which only merits the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Temporal puniſhment? and how this merit diſtinguiſh't from the reſt is put into the Treaſure? theſe and many other perplexities are ſo intervowen in this Doctrine that their wiſeſt <hi>Doctors</hi> have not yet found out a way to extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The authority diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theſe Indulgences <hi>(i. e.)</hi> The Council ſuppoſe this for granted that there was a power left to the Church of beſtowing theſe Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the Church hath from all Antiquity uſed it: but if theſe things be uncertain, then we have
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49882:59"/> no reaſon to own this Doctrine. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſay there is no Certainty, that Chriſt left this power to the Church, they tell us, that the Pope onely hath power of beſtowing thoſe Indulgences <hi>Jure Divino:</hi> Biſhops and other Prelates <hi>Jure humano:</hi> that the Pope may grant plenary Indulgences <note n="*" place="margin">Sum. Angel. c. 1. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. n. 5.</note> and over all the world: that his power is founded in theſe words, <hi>what ever thou looſeſt on earth ſhall be looſed in Heaven;</hi> and on that text <hi>feed my Sheep</hi> in which is included all acts of Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which any way conduce to ſhut or open the Kingdome of Heaven, and of this ſort is remiſſion of puniſhment by theſe Indulgences; <note n="†" place="margin">Filliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3. n. 62<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but this is wholy uncertain, and founded rather on meere gueſſes, than on a rational ground: For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is not certain that he who can remit the Eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as they tell us the Prieſt doth in the Sacrament of Penance) cannot alſo remit the Temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhment: becauſe he who can do
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49882:59"/> the greater, regularly) unleſs there be ſome reſtraint) can do the leſs. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not certain, that the Pope hath any power of gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe Indulgences from thoſe texts, for it's neither expreſt in the texts, nor gathered thence by anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Interpreters,</hi> nor is it evident by fair conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not certain, that the Church hath uſed them from all <hi>antiquity,</hi> for where will they find the Popes <hi>divine</hi> right of granting Indulgences. That theſe Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were remiſſions of temporal pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to God? that by the remiſſion of theſe puniſhments here ſo much was abated as they muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in this life or in Purgatory; that there were Indulgences for 100, or 1000, of yeares? that for repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Prayer over hallowed <hi>Beads</hi> viſiting ſuch an <hi>Altar</hi> praying before ſuch an <hi>Image!</hi> there ſhould be granted an Indulgence <hi>toties quoties,</hi> either of all, or halfe or third part of their ſins? as many Buls of modern
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49882:60"/> Popes ſpeak: and ꝑo. <hi>Cajetane</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. c. 1.</note> will tel us that neither the Holy Scripture nor the writings of the ancient <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers brought this to our knowledge, but only à 300 annis <hi>Scripturae Commendatum eſt de veteribus patribus, quod Beatus Gregorius Indulgentias Stationum in: ſtituit:</hi> it was Committed to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about 300 years ago, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ancient Fathers, that St. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> ordained the Indulgences of the <hi>Stations:</hi> ſome tell us there are no manifeſt Teſtimonies before St. <hi>Gregorys</hi> time, yet we muſt believe (though we have no ground for it I warrant you) ſaies <hi>Angelus de Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſio</hi> that they were in uſe before: others confeſs, <hi>there is nothing the Scripture doth leſs plainly deliver, or the ancient Fathers leſs mention,</hi> so <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro: that they began when Charity leſſned, and ſin increaſed,</hi> ſay others: yea ſome will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, becauſe the uſe of them ſeems to be late, and lately found out among the Chriſtians, ſales
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49882:60"/> 
               <hi>Roffenſis</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ad Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18.</note> and all he Anſwers, is this, that there was ſome uſe (as they ſay) among the ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and that many things are now found out more plainly, out of the Goſpels, and other Scriptures than were heretofore: if thus they are not agreed who wrote before the Council, concerning the Antiquity of them, nor are there any evident Teſtimonies in the <hi>Fathers</hi> or anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Writers of ſuch uſe of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as they now practice, it is then not certain that the Church hath from all Antiquity uſed them, and ꝑo. I have no reaſon to aſſent to this Doctrine of Indulgences delivered by the Council.</p>
            <p>This is my firſt Argument to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade from reunion with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Romiſh Church, becauſe many of their Doctrines, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to be believed as Articles of Faith, are uncertain and doubtfull.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:49882:61"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <p>THe ſecond <hi>Conſideration</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> drawn from the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church: It is unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to adhere to that Church which commands us <hi>firmly</hi> to embrace thoſe for <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> rites, which are altogether queſtionable, and dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and thoſe for pious, and good, which it is doubtfull, whether they be not vain, rediculous, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious: but the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church commands this: ꝑo. In the Creed of <hi>Pius</hi> 4. it is required, <hi>That they ſhould moſt firmly admit, and embrace the Apoſtolical, and Eccleſiaſtical Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other obſervations of that Church,</hi> and afterwards, <hi>that they receive, and admit the approved rites of Catholick</hi> (as they call the <hi>Roman Church) in the ſolemn adminiſtration of the ſeven Sacraments:</hi> and its decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Council, <hi>that the Church hath uſed in the Sacrifice of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:49882:61"/> ceremonies as miſtical bleſſings, Lights, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neenſe, Garments, and many other things from Apoſtolical Diſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne and Tradition.</hi> But many things which they affirm to be Apoſtolical are at beſt uncertain, and many things which they require thus firmly to be believed are vain, and fooliſh, and cannot be excuſed from all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is uncertain, that many of thoſe ceremonies which they uſe in the Maſs are of Apoſtolical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Tradition as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is no certainty that their miſtical bleſſings are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered down from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for though we are bound to receive the creatures with thanksgiving, and by prayer to God they are bleſſed for that uſe which he hath appointed, yet it is uncertain whether the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did leave this Tradition, that certain things ſhould be bleſſed by prayer, and the ſigne of the <hi>Croſs</hi> to work ſupernatural effects, as to cure diſeaſes, and drive away Devils, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49882:62"/> remit venial ſins, which things <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">L. 2. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffect. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ram. c. 31. prop. 3.</note> makes the effect of theſe benedictions. In the bleſſing of the wax lights on E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter eve (this muſt be done by a <hi>Deacon,</hi> and he muſt put five grains of hallowed incenſe into it after the faſhion of a Croſs) he exhorts all to invoke the mercy of God, that he who vouchſafed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit into the number of <hi>Levites,</hi> powring on him the clearneſs of his light, would inable him to perfect the prayſes of that wax light, <hi>cerei hujus laudem implere perficiat:</hi> and then prayes <hi>that this taper may remain conſtantly to deſtroy the miſt of this night, and being accepted for a ſweet ſmell may be mingled with the Heavenly lights.</hi> In the bleſſing of holy water the Prieſt exorcizes the fact to be for the health of believers, and to all that take it ſoundneſs of ſoul, and body, and that all wickedneſs, and cunning of <hi>devils</hi> may fly from the place where it is ſprinkled: and he exorcizes the water to drive away the power of the devil, and to root
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49882:62"/> out the enemy with the apoſtate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: and again prays, that this crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſerving theſe miſteries, may receive the effect of the divine grace to drive away devils and expell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, &amp;c <note n="*" place="margin">Miſſal. <hi>Rom.</hi> in Bened. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quae.</note>. In the bleſſing of holy bread, he prays that God would bleſs it with holy ſpiritual bleſſing, <hi>that it may be to all that receive it, health of Soul, and Body, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt all diſeaſes, and all the ſnares of the enemies</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Miſſal. <hi>Rom.</hi> in Bened. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note>. So in the bleſſing of Candles, he prays, <hi>that they may receive ſuch bleſſing by the ſigne of the Croſs, that in what ever places they are lighted, the Princes of darkneſs may depart, and tremble, and fly away with all his Servants from all thoſe habitations</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Miſſal. <hi>Rom</hi> in Benedict. Cand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</note>. In the bleſſing of the Croſs, he prays, that God would bleſs that wood of the Croſs, <hi>ut ſit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medium ſalutare generi humano, ſit ſoliditas fidei bonorum operum profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, &amp; redemptio animarum,</hi> &amp;c. That it may be a wholeſome remedy for mankind, it may be firmneſs of faith, increaſe of good works, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49882:63"/> of Souls, and defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the cruel darts of the devil <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſpin.</hi> de Orig. Templ. l. 4. c. 4.</note>. Theſe are miſtical bleſſings which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church uſes, and which they pretend are derived from Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Diſcipline, and Tradition, but it is uncertain, whether ever the Apoſtles did bleſſe thoſe Creatures for ſuch ſupernatural ends? and whether they did leave either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or example which ſhould warrant the Church in after ages to bleſs any Creatures for the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſuch Effects? if it be certain, then they muſt produce ſome text of Scripture, ſo interpreted by the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous conſent of the Fathers, as the profeſſion of faith by <hi>Pius</hi> 4. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: or ſome conſtant Tradition delivered down through the ſeveral ages of the Church: but neither of theſe can be done; for, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their own Authors have affix'd the Inſtitution of theſe ſeveral forms of bleſſing to the times long after the Apoſtles, and ꝑo. it cannot be ſaid that the Church hath received them
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49882:63"/> from Apoſtolical diſcipline and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: the bleſſing of the <hi>Paſchal</hi> taper is pretended to be the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Zozimus</hi> and <hi>Theodore</hi> the firſt, who ſate <hi>anno</hi> 640; the form of bleſſing to be dictated by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and that <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> a Monk of <hi>Caſſino</hi> compoſed others which are out of uſe, as <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rasie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale Div. Offic. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 80.</note> tells us; but whether the ſame forme? or any ſuch kind of forme as is now in uſe? or whether any at all? we can have no certainty from Authors, who lived ſome hundred years aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Till ꝑo. they can certainly prove, not only that a <hi>Paſchal</hi> taper was uſed in the Church, but that it was uſed from the Apoſtles times, and uſed for this end with ſuch like form of bleſſing as is now practiced by the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> I do not ſee how the Council can declare this to be an article of faith that it came from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical diſcipline and Tradition: the bleſſing of holy water was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced (ſay the moſt of them) by <hi>Alexander</hi> the firſt, ſo ſay
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49882:64"/> 
               <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ional. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4</note>, <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum l.</hi> 5. 68.</note>, and <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> in the life of <hi>Alexander</hi> the firſt, and yet this higher, than we can be certain of it: for there is no certainty of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> aſcribed to <hi>Alexander,</hi> whence they fetch this Inſtitution, nor of the <hi>Pontifical</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to <hi>Damaſus</hi> as <hi>Reynolds</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Lib. Apoc. Pra-lect.</hi> 179, 180.</note> ſhews from the acknowledgment of many of their own authors. The bleſſing of bread for driving away devils, (if we believe <hi>Abdias</hi> a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Author l. 2. Hiſtor. Apoſt.) is derived from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Gavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Theſ. Sacr. Rit. Part. 4. Tit. 19. n. 19.</note> tells us: but what certainty have we of this Tradition, when we have no certainty even by their own confeſſion of the truth, and honeſty of this author? and if we believe him, when all antiquity is ſilent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, he had need be <hi>teſtis omni exceptione major:</hi> beſides this, the firſt bleſſing which <hi>Gavantus</hi> could bring was from <hi>Gregory's</hi> Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, about 600 years after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and ꝑo. ſtill no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty that it was from Apoſtolical
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49882:64"/> Tradition: for the bleſſing of candles, they tell us <hi>Sergius</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a proceſſion with hallowed candles on the feaſt of the Purificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuppoſE the Inſtitution higher, as <hi>Baronius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirelogi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> doth, who fathers it on <hi>Eligius,</hi> who died <hi>anno</hi> 665, yet ſtill ſhort enough of the Apoſtles times: if thus their own authors who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely inquire their Antiquities, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign their inſtitution after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles daies, then it is not certain, that the Church received them from Apoſtolical Tradition: unleſs we can believe that rare expoſition which ſome <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gavant</hi> Theſ. Sacr. Rit. p. 4. Tit. 19. n. 2.</note> give of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words to <hi>Timothy, 2 Tim. 1. 13. Formam habe ſanorum verborum quae à me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciſti. Sanorum, (i. e.) quae poſſunt ſanare ſenſibiles &amp; inſenſibiles creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> that the forme of ſound words was the forme of bleſſings for ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural effects; but ſuch Interpretations, I ſuppoſe the ſoberer <hi>Romaniſts</hi> will ſooner deride, than believe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is no way certain that they received the uſe of lights
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49882:65"/> from Apoſtolical Tradition: the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> requires at <hi>Maſs</hi> the candels to be lighted, and though it be midday, yet allows no Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration without it: but now, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Though the Apoſtles might uſe lights at the time of Divine Service, when they were forced to meet in Grotts, and Caves, and darke places, and commonly in the night <hi>(caetibus antelucanis)</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> obſerved, to avoid the danger of perſecution: yet there is no certainty that we are obliged by that example to light up Candles in the Day, nor any certainty that they left that rule for after Ages. <hi>Secondly,</hi> though the Church after the times of Perſecution did uſe lights to ſhew themſelves the Succeſſors of pious men, yet it's not certain that this was a neceſſary but voluntary imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> as for thoſe ancients who pleaded for the Continuance of lights ti's no way certain, that they uſed them to expel devils or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any ſupernatural virtue in them
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49882:65"/> but only as ſignes of joy, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of Chriſt, as <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Div O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic. l. 1. c. 1. tit. S.</note> gives us their miſtical ſignification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is no way certain, that they received the uſe of Incenſe from Apoſtolical Tradition; for, <hi>Firſt,</hi> though Incenſe might have been uſed in the Primitive Church either for ſome miſtical ſignification, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> mentions three mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious reaſons, or <hi>ad tetrum odorem ſiquis ex multudine in Eccleſià exiſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, abigendum;</hi> to drive away thoſe Filthy ſmels which might be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the concourſe of people, which is the moſt likely reaſon; for the Chriſtians being forced to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſubterranious Cels, and Caves, they might uſe incenſe to prevent the infection, which they might fear from the vapors in dark, and low places: but it is not certain, that they uſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe on the ſame reaſon it is now uſed by the <hi>Romaniſts, ut omnes languores Cunctaeque inſidiae inimici odorem ejus ſentientes effugiant, &amp; ſeperentur à plaſmate tuo, &amp;c.</hi> That all faintings
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49882:66"/> and treacheries of the devils percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this ſmel may fly away, and be removed from the workmanſhip which thou haſt redeemed by thy precious blood, and that they may never be hurt by the biting of the ancient Serpent <note n="*" place="margin">Instit: Baptiz. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. uſum. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in hened. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſi.</note> Though the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients might uſe Incenſe for ſweetning the places of their aſſemblies, yet it is uncertain, that they uſed it for devotion to drive away the devils temptations. The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church requires at the Celebration of the <hi>Maſs</hi> the cenſing of the <hi>Altar,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpels</hi> which muſt be done three times, and the <hi>Elements</hi> which are to be conſecrated, drawing the Cenſer thrice upon the <hi>Hoſt</hi> and <hi>Chalice</hi> together in the faſhion of a <hi>Croſſe,</hi> and thrice round about them <hi>(i. e.)</hi> twice from the right hand to the left, and once from the left hand to the right <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rubr. General. in offert. Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</hi> Pii. 5.</note>. after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he muſt cenſe the Croſs and the Altar again, then the Deacon cenſes the Prieſt, afterward he cenſes the Quire and the ſub-Deacon, then
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49882:66"/> the cenſer bearer cenſes the Deacon, then the Acolites, laſtly the People <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rubr. Genera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in offert. c. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 10.</note>. And all this is done to drive away devils, ſaies <hi>Innocent</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>l. 2. c.</hi> 17.</note> the third in his expoſition of the Maſs: and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Com. in Rubr. Miſſae. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 2. tit. 4. n. 4. l. ic. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from him: but by what record? or what ground ſhall I be certain that the Apoſtles comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this? or that their Church in conformity to the practice of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles did thus? or Laſtly, that the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church pretends no other virtue, or efficacy in Incenſe, than was allowed by the ancient Church. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I have further reaſon to queſtion the uncertainty of this pretended Tradition, for even ſeveral authors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion have affixed a far latter date to the beginning of this Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Platina</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">In vitâ Sixti. 1.</note>, and <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. l. 5. c.</hi> 10.</note> refer it to <hi>Leo</hi> the third who was the 98th Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> according to <hi>Platina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is no way certain, that they received the uſe of <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Garments from <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Tradition,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49882:67"/> though we do not contend whether the Prieſt may uſe diſtinct Garments in the Celebration, for the practice is according to St. <hi>Hierome's</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>Religio divina alterum habet habitum in miniſterio alternm in uſu, vitâque communi,</hi> that their habits in their miniſtration were diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from thoſe they commonly uſed: yet we judge theſe are <hi>liberae Inſtitutionis,</hi> which are indifferent in themſelves, and not abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: ſuch things as the Church may injoyne from its own authority in things indifferent, not which it muſt injoyne from Apoſtolical command. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> We are no way certain that the Apoſtles practiced or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſuch things, that either at the firſt Inſtitution by our Saviour, or at the Celebration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Apoſtles they uſed any ſuch Prieſtly Garments: and ꝑo. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">De In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. c. 7.</note> ſaies, <hi>Hebraica magis quam Apoſtolica referunt inſtituta,</hi> they more reſemble the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> than <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitutions. Secondly,</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:49882:67"/> We are not certain, that though God did appoint in the <hi>Old</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch habits for <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, when they were to miniſter, the Prieſts ꝑo. in the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament muſt have ſuch: for all agree, that nothing preſcribed in the <hi>Moſaical</hi> miniſtration doth bind us Chriſtians, unleſs where the nature of it is <hi>Moral,</hi> elſe we ſhould be obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all the Rites annd Ceremonys which <hi>Moſes</hi> appointed: and ꝑo. it ſeems very ſtrange that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. 2. de Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. c.</hi> 14.</note> ſhould ſay, that the Garments of the <hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſts were Figures, and Types of thoſe Veſtments which the Chriſtians uſe: for to repreſent and tipify ſomething to be uſed in the times of the Goſpel requires a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution: but it is no way certain that they were ſo appointed by Divine Inſtitution, ꝑo. we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aſſert that they are Figures and Types of the Prieſtly Veſtments which are now uſed. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If we look on the ſeveral habits which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to their <hi>Clergy,</hi> we ſhall think
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49882:68"/> it very unlikely, that they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Apoſtles, either if we conſider the things required, or the ſignifications they aſſign to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As for the things required, there are ſix things required in the attire of a Prieſt, but 15 ſeveral parts of the attire of a Biſhop as <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ration. Div. Offic. l. 3. c. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it.</hi> G. H.</note> reckons them: and though the High Prieſt among the <hi>Jewes</hi> had only eight things in his attire, yet the Biſhop muſt have fifteen, becauſe (forſooth) as <hi>Durand</hi> gives the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate reaſon, our righteouſneſs muſt exceed the righteouſnes of <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſes.</hi> Nay theſe fifteen are not all, for beſides theſe he wears his <hi>Surpliſs</hi> and his <hi>pluviale:</hi> now it's very improbable, that the Apoſtles ſhould require more than <hi>Moſes</hi> did, or that when they impoſed ſuch ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral habits, that yet neither in the Scripture nor Primitive writers, there appear the leaſt footſtep of this injunction. <hi>Secondly,</hi> If we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the grounds they pretend, and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49882:68"/> the ſignification they give them, it will ſeem altogether improbable that they ſhould be derived from the Apoſtles. The <hi>Sandals</hi> (ſay they) come from the Apoſtles who uſed Sandals, <hi>Mark,</hi> 6 9. But if the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles example there be a ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, then they muſt neither have a Staff in their Journy, nor Mony in their Purſe: or if they pretend our Saviours command, Go, teach all nations, which reaſon <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rationale Div. Offic. l. 3. c. 8. tit.</hi> A.</note> gives, that will never ſute with the grandeur of their Biſhops, nor yet with their practice, who do not uſe to foot it, to Preach in their own Cures. The Miter (ſaies <hi>Baronius</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. 34. n.</hi> 298.</note>) came from the Apoſtles, and the Biſhop with his Miter repreſents <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from the Mount with the 2 Tables: but if it came from the Apoſtles, how comes it to have 2 Horns? becauſe (ſay they) <hi>Moſes</hi> when he came from the Mount was Horned <note n="*" place="margin">Polyd. Virgil. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Invent. Rer. l. 4. c.</hi> 7.</note>; an error which the <hi>vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> Tranſlation has occaſion'd by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreting a word. For where it
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49882:69"/> ſhould be read his face ſhone. That tranſlation renders it <hi>cornuta erat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ejus, Exod.</hi> 34. 2. and yet here's an Apoſtolical Tradition pretended to juſtifie their miſtake. But this is not all, why muſt it be Horned? to note (ſaies <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rationale Div. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. l. 3. c. 13. tit. C. D.</note>) the 2 Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: why muſt the <hi>Miter</hi> have two ſtays hanging behind? to note (ſaies he) the Spirit and the letter. Why muſt it be made high? to note the eminency of knowledge which muſt be in a Biſhop: the <hi>Gloves</hi> (ſaies <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">161. l. 13. c. 12.</note>) muſt be put on according to the Tradition of the Apoſtles, next after the <hi>Dalmatica</hi> that his left hand may not know what his right hand doth. And why Gloves to cover their hands? becauſe workes muſt be publick, but the intention ſecret <note n="*" place="margin">Gavant. <hi>Theſ. Sacr. Rit. Part 2 tit. 1. pag.</hi> 99.</note>: why muſt he ſometimes put them off and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times put them on? becauſe good works muſt ſometimes be ſecret to ſhun vain glory, ſometimes publick to edefy their neighbours. (Saies <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand)</hi> will ye ſee more of theſe five
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49882:69"/> reaſons which their <hi>Ritualiſts</hi> give concerning <hi>Prieſtly,</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits; and you will then think that thoſe who pretend to give a reaſon of thoſe Ceremonies do only <hi>inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire cum ratione,</hi> and that 'tis very unlike the ſimplicity of Religion which the Apoſtles delivered. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I add that 'tis ſo far from being certain, that theſe Garments came from the Apoſtles, that their own authors tell us, that at firſt they ſaid Maſs in their uſual Garments, ſo <hi>Gavantus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part. 1. tit.</hi> 18.</note> out of <hi>Walafrid Strabo,</hi> and that by degrees the multitude of theſe habits which are now uſed, were brought in <note n="†" place="margin">Gavant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>61.</note>. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> 'Tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain whether the authors of the greateſt antiquity aſſert, what they affix to them: for ſome aſcribe this to <hi>Clement,</hi> that he according to Tradition from St. <hi>Peter</hi> did inſtitute theſe holy Veſtments, but there is no certainty of this pretended Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, nor of this pretended Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: ſome aſcribe it to <hi>Anaclet,</hi> antiquity enough if it could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49882:70"/> (whether he be the ſame with <hi>Cletus,</hi> whom ſome make a Coad ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> or that there were ſuch an one who was immediate ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to <hi>Clement)</hi> but we muſt be firſt ſure of the authority, before we believe the Teſtimony: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. l. 2. c.</hi> 14.</note> durſt not call theſe decretal Epiſtles undoubted, though he believed them ancient: but there needs no more proof of the ſpuriouſneſs of this Epiſtle father'd on <hi>Anaclet;</hi> than to obſerve the Barberous expreſſions in it, and thoſe names it mentions, which were of a later Original <note n="‡" place="margin">Blondel. <hi>Ceuſ. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. in</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clet. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist.</hi> 1.</note> Thus I have handled the firſt part of my argument from the Rites, and Ceremonies of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, that for many of theſe things they require us to profeſs, to be of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Diſcipline, and Tradition, it is wholly uncertain, whether they be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is not certain, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church be not vain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and inexcuſable from <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition:</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49882:70"/> I will not inſtance in the cuſtoms of particular Churches, and places. As in the manner of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of <hi>Innocents</hi> day by the <hi>Epiſcopus puerorum</hi> in the Church of <hi>Salisbury:</hi> in the ſtrange cuſtome which Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Opuſe. Posth. in his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe de Epiſc. pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erorum.</note> produces from the Ritual of <hi>Oſny</hi> Abby of the foot of a Child, which was uſually kept in a Cheſt in the Veſtry, and that day was carried about the Church to be adored by the people. In the cuſtom of the <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gick</hi> Churches to take up a man on <hi>Aſcention</hi> day, thereby to repreſent Chriſts aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſend down a <hi>Dove</hi> in repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt on <hi>Whit-Sunday,</hi> as the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitates Liturgicae</hi> tells us <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Yom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in Sabbate Sancto de Caer. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch. Duaci.</hi> 1065.</note>. I will not inſtance in ſuch cuſtomes, though many may be produced, becauſe the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> will grant, the cuſtomes of particular Churches may be vain, and ſuperſtitious: ꝑo. the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> doth only require that we ſhould imbrace the Rites of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church: and appoints a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49882:71"/> of thoſe abuſes which might have crept in, as in the number of Candles on <hi>Eaſter</hi> eve, ſome (ſaies <hi>Durand)</hi> have 72 Candles, ſome 24, ſome 15, ſome 12, and all theſe pretend ſome miſtery: now the Council provides againſt the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious number of Candles; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> 5. prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Roman</hi> Miſſal, all other Rites and Ceremonies in other Miſſals (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs where there is a preſcription of 200 years) are abrogated. So that my buſineſs is to prove, that there are many Ceremonies univerſally practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church or allowed in ſome particular Churches, which are vain, unprofitable, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable from ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I inſtance in the many Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of bleſſing the <hi>Font,</hi> the recital of which is a ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their vanity: one Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is the dividing the water after the faſhion of a Croſs, and that is done that the water may be fruitfull
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49882:71"/> through the holy Spirit, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean one expel'd <note n="*" place="margin">Miſſal. <hi>Pii 5.</hi> in Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. Fontis.</note>: again, he muſt touch the water with his hand, that by the Invocation of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> the water may be defended, leaſt the divel return <note n="†" place="margin">Durand. <hi>Rationale l. 6. c.</hi> 82.</note>: again, he divides the water with his hand, and caſts the water towards the foure parts of the World: another Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is the changing of the Tone, which muſt be done thrice, after the manner of a prayer he muſt ſpeak low, then he muſt raiſe his voice af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of their Prefaces, then he muſt let fall his voice after the manner of reading the Leſſons: but why muſt the voice be changed thrice? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t in Trinitate omnia fiant</hi> ſaies <hi>Gavantus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Part. 4. Tit. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 25.</note>: another Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is the breathing on the water three times after the faſhion of a Croſs, and leaſt that ſhould not do the work, he muſt blow thrice upon it after the manner of the Greek let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to denote the Trinity, that he may joyne the Trinity with the Croſs <note n="†" place="margin">Gavant. 161. <hi>n.</hi> 26.</note>: but what will this blowing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49882:72"/> do? they'l tell you (if you believe them) the devil is blown away with a breath and they blow in contempt of him; as if the devil could not withſtand a blaſt: There is another Ceremony the putting the paſchal taper into the Font, which muſt be firſt a little way and the Prieſt ſaies, <hi>Deſcendat in han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plenitudinem Fontis Spiritus Sancti virtus,</hi> let the virtue of the holy Ghoſt deſcend upon the fullneſs of the Font: but will ye know the reaſon of this Ceremony, it is to ſignify the ſpirits deſcending with his fullneſs into the Font, as he deſcended at the baptiſme of our Saviour in likeneſs of a Dove <note n="*" place="margin">Gavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus 161. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 27.</note>; this taper then muſt be taken out, to note the effect of baptiſme, which raiſes from ſin to glory, then the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per muſt be put lower into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Prieſt raiſe his voice, the third time the taper muſt be put to the bottome, and the Prieſt repeat the prayer <hi>(Deſcendat in hanc,</hi> &amp;c.) lowder. I omit the reſt of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonics, for I need not render the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49882:72"/> office more ridiculous, by repeating more of the like nature: and if there be ſo little reaſon for the inſtitution of them, and ſuch antickneſs in the performance of them, we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to judge that it is at the beſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, whether they be not vain, and unprofitable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I inſtance in many Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies uſed in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> I do not condemn every Ceremony in it, for ſome of them were very anciently uſed, ſome may not be unfit to ſignifie either ſome duty, or ſome priviledge: and theſe are not condemned by us, where they may ſerve to a decent order, and godly diſcipline, and may have any aptneſs to ſtirre up the mind of man by ſome notable ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to the remembrance of his duty <note n="*" place="margin">Book of Common prayer Pref. of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</note>, and while they are as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> advices <hi>pauc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſalubres.</hi> I paſs by the number of their Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies in Baptiſm, which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaies are 22, and only conſider, that many of theſe either have no ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49882:73"/> to excite us by a fit ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or elſe are uſed not only for ſignification, but extraordinary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration: now theſe things cannot produce by an extraordinary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, unleſs by the virtue and influx of a ſuperior agent: and where there is no aſſurance of any aſſiſtance from ſuch a ſuperior agent, theſe Ceremonies muſt be vain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, and ſuperſtitious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some of them have no ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to excite us by a fit ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I paſs by the Ceremony of putting ſalt into the infants mouth, yet I may wonder whence the Prieſt hath authority to ſay, take the ſalt of wiſdome, that God may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to thee unto Eternal life. Or what ground to pray that he who taſts this food of ſalt may not hunger more, as if it was equall to that Heavenly bread which our Saviour promiſed, of which whoever eats ſhall live for ever, <hi>John</hi> 6. 58. I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Ceremony of ſpittle, that the Prieſt muſt ſpit on his left hand,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49882:73"/> and put the ſpittle into the eares and noſe of the Infant with his right thumb, ſaying to the right eare, <hi>Epphata</hi> be thou opened, he muſt ſay to the noſe for a ſweet ſmell: and to the left eare be thou driven away O devil, for the judgement of God approaches: but why muſt he ſay to the eare be thou opened? and why doth he touch the noſe with ſpittle and put his finger into the eares? <hi>Durand</hi> wants no reaſon (as he thinks he muſt touch the noſe that it might receive the odor of the knowledge of God, he muſt touch the eares to hear the commands of God, the fingers put into the eares muſt repreſent the words, or gifts of the holy Spirit. He muſt touch the eares with ſpittle, to ſignifie the words proceeding from the mouth of the higheſt, which enter through the eares, and ſmel ſweet to him: the noſtrills muſt be touched, that they may receive divine virtue, by which they may diſtinguiſh a good ſmel from a bad, and ſeperate ſound
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49882:74"/> Doctrine from Heretical pravity <note n="*" place="margin">Durand <hi>Rational. l. 6. c. 8. lit.</hi> R.</note>: if we think theſe to be far fetched reaſons, I wonder how they firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented ſuch inſignificant, vain Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> will retort on us our Saviours practice, how he touched the mans tongue, and eares who was deaf and dumb. <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 32, 33. and cured the blinde mans eyes with clay and ſpittle, <hi>John</hi> 9. 6. and yet he could have cured without thoſe Ceremonies: well, but what is this Ceremony to our Saviours practice? what he uſed in the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the deaf and blinde, they uſe to them who are neither deaf nor blinde: if our Saviour uſed it in the producing a miraculous effect, is it not ludicrous for them to uſe it in imitation of him, where they do not pretend to imitate him in working the effect? if then, there's no apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſignifie nor proper reaſon can be aſſigned of their Inſtitution, then they are vain and un profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us ſee thoſe <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:49882:74"/> which are uſed not only for ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, but the effecting of ſome thing: the Child muſt be <hi>Croſt</hi> ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, and in ſeveral places on his <hi>forehead,</hi> on his <hi>breaſt</hi> and on his <hi>right</hi> hand, and that not <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally</hi> for ſignification, as <hi>that they are not aſhamed to confeſs the faith of Chriſt crucified,</hi> but for <hi>the effecting ſome wonderfull thing,</hi> as <hi>driving out the devil,</hi> ſo in the order for making <hi>Catecumens</hi> when the Prieſt ſignes him on the right hand, he ſaies, <hi>I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee the Seal of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in thy right hand that thou may'ſt ſigne thy ſelf, and defend thee from the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and abide in the Catholick faith, and live for ever:</hi> If this will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, there is another thing, that the Child muſt be anointed with <hi>Oyle</hi> on the breſt, and on the ſhoulder bones <hi>with the Oyle of Salvation in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that thou may ſt have Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life:</hi> and the effect of this Oyle is for purging of his ſins, and defence from the devil <note n="*" place="margin">Durand <hi>Rationale l. 6. c. 71. lit.</hi> L.</note>. I paſs by the white garment which is put on the Infant,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49882:75"/> Or the burning <hi>taper</hi> put into his hand, becauſe as they are barely <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificative,</hi> we leave them among in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things, which every Church may injoyne, as ſhe judges them uſefull for decency, and edification. But there is one rare thing behind, a receit againſt the falling ſickneſs <note n="*" place="margin">Inst. Baptiz. &amp; ſec. uſum Sarum. in fine Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſmi.</note>, <hi>The Prieſt may ſay a Goſpel over the Child, if he will, which (the Doctors ſay) is very effectual, and that is out of St. Mark concerning the curing of of the Child, which was ſometimes thrown into the fire and ſometimes into the water;</hi> and the like ground <hi>Fitz-Simon</hi> gives of the reading of the firſt of St. <hi>John</hi> after the ending of the Maſs, becauſe many had found it effectual againſt ſome diſeaſes, with which they had been afflicted: ꝑo. the Prieſt to ſatisfie all mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires uſed to conclude the Maſs with the Goſpel. Now I aske what aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance can we have that thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies which themſelves invent, have ſuch power to effect theſe things? what certainty that the firſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49882:75"/> of St. <hi>John</hi> read, which the people do not underſtand, is more effectuall than the firſt of St. <hi>John</hi> tied about their necks? and whether to aſcribe ſuch effects to them, which are above their nature where there is neither divine command, nor promiſe can be cleared from ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I inſtance in the bleſſing of <hi>Bells</hi> out of the Inſtit. <hi>Baptizandi, &amp;c. ſecundum uſum Sarum:</hi> when the metal is running, the Prieſt put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on his <hi>Surplis,</hi> and <hi>Stole</hi> the <hi>Croſs</hi> going before him with the Clergy, and people, they ſing the Himn <hi>Veni Creator:</hi> when it is finiſht, they ſing the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and in the end <hi>Da Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem,</hi> with ſome verſicles: before it is hung, it muſt be bleſſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, and ꝑo. firſt he prays <note n="*" place="margin">Inst. Bapt. ſec. uſum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. in Bened. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpan. Orat. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> over the holy water, with which it is ſprinckled, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t cum hoc vaſculum ad invitandos Eccleſiae Filios praeparatum. in eâ fuerit tinctum, ubicunque hoc ſonuerit tintinnabulum, longè recedat virtus inimicorum,</hi> &amp;c. that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49882:76"/> this Bell ſounds, the power of enemies, the ſhadows of apparitions, the fury of whirlewinds, ſtriking of thunderbolts, calamities of tempeſts, and every ſperit of ſtormes may be gone: then he muſt waſh it with holy water, hallowed oyle, and ſalt, and ſay this Prayer, that God who Commanded by <hi>Moſes</hi> ſilver Trumpets to be made, which the <hi>Levites</hi> ſhould ſound at the time of Sacrifice, and the people admoniſht by their ſweetneſs be prepared to worſhip thee, &amp;c. Would grant that this veſſel prepared for the uſe of his Church, might be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the holy ſperit, that by the ſound of it the faithful might be invited to their reward, and when the melody of it ſounds in their eares, their devotion may increaſe, the treacheries of the enemy may be driven away, the ſounds of haile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, the ſtorme of whirle winds, and the violence of tempeſts may be moderated, &amp;c. then he muſt wipe it with a towel, ſaying the 28th
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49882:76"/> 
               <hi>Pſalme,</hi> after this he muſt touch it with <hi>Chryſme</hi> 7 times on the out ſide and 4 times on the inſide, ſaying <hi>O Almighty God who madeſt Stone walls to fall before the Ark of the Covenant, by the ſound of Trumpets, poure out thy bleſſing on this Bell, that the fiery darts of the enemy, the ſhaking of Thunder may be driven far off, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſound of it:</hi> and in another prayer, <hi>that the enemies army may be affrighted, the people cal'd by it may be comforted in the Lord, and the holy Spirit even as it was delighted with Davids Harpe may deſcend upon them:</hi> then the Bell muſt be ſprinckled with holy water, and the Prieſt muſt name it, laying his hands upon it, and ſo muſt the <hi>Godfathers</hi> and <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers,</hi> who muſt name it after the Prieſt, and cover it with Linnen cloaths, and after this <hi>benediction</hi> the Bell becomes ſo holy that no man muſt Tole it, unleſs he wear a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Surplis,</hi> ſaies <hi>Gavantus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part. 1. ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20.</note> from a Council of <hi>Colen.</hi> This is their ſtrange way of bleſſing Bells, which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49882:77"/> almoſt needs no other refutation, than bare recital of the manner of it: for what reaſon of anointing within and without? or if it was no more than in imitation of the <hi>Jewes</hi> to ſeperate this for an holy uſe, yet why 7 times on the outſide, and 4 times on the inſide, why muſt this be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo that it may gather up all the ſmoak? and why muſt it be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in ſo ſolemn a manner? what uſe of <hi>Godfathers</hi> and <hi>Godmothers</hi> here, of laying their hands on it, afterwards of covering it with Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloathes, which is an imitation of that Ceremony of the white garment they uſed in Baptiſm? and why do they pray that their ſound may drive away devils, frighten enemies, hinder ſtorms, &amp;c? as by the ſound of Trumpets the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> fell down: for there was both a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhould blow the Trumpets, and a promiſe of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary bleſſing: here is no ground to pretend either command, or promiſe.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:49882:77"/>
            <p>I might Inſtance in their ſtrange forms of exorcizing perſons poſſeſſed with devils, the vanity of which is ſufficiently deſcribed by my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Downe</hi> in his excellent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive from Popery, for they rather ſeem like magical Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than devout formes of prayer.</p>
            <p>I might Inſtance in their conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Chryſme,</hi> how it muſt be brought from the <hi>Veſtry</hi> to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> by 12 <hi>Prieſts</hi> repreſenting the 12 <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> and by other <hi>Clergy</hi> men ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> how after it is bleſſed it muſt be ſaluted by the Biſhop and his Prieſts 5 times with a lowd voice <hi>ave Sanctum Chryſma</hi> hayle holy Chriſme; and how the Biſhop muſt breath 3 times on it, as <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rational. l. 6. c.</hi> 74.</note> gives us the forme. I could inſtance in their ſtrange formes of proceſſions with anticks going before them, as if they intended rather to Create laughter, than ſtir up Devotion: a cuſtome which <hi>Polidor Virgil</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>de Invent. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 6. c.</hi> 11.</note> confeſſes was without
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49882:78"/> doubt received from the heatheniſh <hi>Romans.</hi> I could Inſtance in their acting of the paſſion, which turns the whole ſeriouſnes of religion into a <hi>mimical</hi> ſport, as <hi>Ludovic Vives</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Dei. l. 8. c. ult.</note> complained: many more of this nature I could reckon up, but theſe are to many.</p>
            <p>The ſum of the ſecond <hi>argument</hi> is this: it is unreaſonable to adhere to that Church, which not only pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices ſuch cerimonies which are vain, and ridiculous, and which is at beſt, uncertain, whether they be not ſuperſtitious, but requires all to owne them for good, and wholeſome: but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth ſo: ꝑo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:49882:78"/>
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <p>MY third <hi>Conſideration</hi> ſhall be drawn from the abſurdities and untruths in ſeveral Offices, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are ſeveral things falſe, many things derogatory from the merits of Chriſt, and aſcribing too much to the Creature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I inſtance in the prayers they make to the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> the Titles they aſcribe to her, and the praiſes they give her. <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the prayers to her: it is certain that a great part of the devotion of the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> is employed in the prayers to her: ſhe hath her <hi>Fices,</hi> ſhe hath her <hi>Houres,</hi> ſhe hath her <hi>Letany,</hi> ſhe hath her <hi>Roſary,</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> 13. Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted a Maſs in honour of the Roſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with Indulgences to them that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate it: ſhe hath her <hi>Pſalter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> which are onely <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms deformed, in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49882:79"/> which the name of <hi>Lady</hi> is put for <hi>Lord,</hi> and what he ſaid of God is aſcribed to the <hi>B. Virgin:</hi> ſhe hath 8 <hi>Feſtivals;</hi> and leaſt they ſhould faile in the performance of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to her, there is a peculiar Maſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Miſſal</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> call'd <hi>Miſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Miſſale ſec. uſum Sarum. an. 1555. in <hi>Vigil.</hi> Paſch.</note> 
               <hi>recollectionis feſtorum B. Mariae.</hi> Let us conſider the prayers themſelves, in which they do not only intreat her to <hi>pray</hi> for them, or <hi>pray</hi> that God would grant their requeſts upon the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> but they deſire that by her merits and prayers they may be brought to Heaven <note n="*" place="margin">Offic. <hi>B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irg.</hi> ad matutin.</note>. And if you think they do not derogate from the <hi>Son</hi> who leane on the <hi>merits</hi> of the <hi>Mother,</hi> you ſhall find them equal'd in a prayer of the Maſs of the moſt holy <hi>Roſary,</hi> where they pray, that God who predeſtinated Jeſus Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh, and choſe the moſt holy Virgin to be his mother, would grant that through both their merits compleated by the 15 ſacred myſteries of the Roſary, we may be ſo for the preſent addicted
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49882:79"/> to them, that we may continually perceive in our ſelves the fruit of them in the glory of an Heavenly life, <hi>praeſta quaeſumus, ut amborum meritis per ſacra 15 myſteria Roſarij completis ità in praeſenti ſimus illis addicti, quatenus in coeleſtis vitae glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fructus eorum jugitur ſentiàmus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſſal.</hi> Rom. <hi>in Miſſ. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarij</hi> Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1631.</note>; nay its well if they do not queſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whether they do not owe more to the Mothers milk, than to the Sons blood, for that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> only a <hi>Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> fancy of <hi>Carolus Scribanius,</hi> but was crept up into a Picture (which they call a Lay mans Book) on a wall in a Church at <hi>Boſledue,</hi> and there found by the <hi>Dutch</hi> at the taking of the Town: from interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhe is got to commanding, and ſhe that acknowledged in the <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat</hi> the lowlineſs of his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, is importuned to command by the authority of a Mother: and if we conſult their Offices there is little can be deſired of our Saviour which they do not ask of her, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o. do not only deſire her interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49882:80"/> for bleſſings, but deſire from her the bleſſings themſelves: in the Himn <hi>Ave Maris ſtella,</hi> which is ſung at the feaſt of the preſentation of <hi>Mary,</hi> they ſay <hi>Solve vincla reis, profer lumen caecis, mala noſtra pelle bona cuncta poſce,</hi> which in the Offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tranſlated into Engliſh is ſomething minced,
<q>
                  <l>The guilty Souls deliver, Light to the Blind reſtoring,</l>
                  <l>Drive hence our Harms for ever, all Good for us imploring;</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But at the prime they go higher, <hi>Maria Mater gratiae mater miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, tu nos ab hoſte protege &amp; in hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mortis ſuſcipe,</hi> which the Engliſh of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice renders,
<q>
                  <l>O Mary Mother whence grace flowes, who Mother of ſweet mercy Art,</l>
                  <l>Protect us from our dangerous foes, receive us when we hence depart:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>What tolerable excuſe can be given
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49882:80"/> for thoſe words, and generous <hi>Mary</hi> obtain pardon for us, apply grace unto us and prepare glory for us <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Hor Beat.</hi> Mariae.</note>. Or that prayer in the Sequence <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Miſſa. Recoll. feſt.</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riae <hi>in Miſſal. Sar.</hi> 1555.</note> (as they call it) <hi>pro nobis obtine genitrix veniam, reatum dilue &amp; dona patriam in arce ſiderum:</hi> procure our pardon, waſh away our guilt, and give us heaven? or for that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Soul to the Virgin <note n="*" place="margin">Office of our Lady in Engliſh.</note>, O holy <hi>Mary</hi> my Lady, I recommend my ſelf unto thy bleſſed truſt, and ſingular cuſtody and into the boſome of thy mercy, this day, and daily, and in the houre of my death, as alſo my Soul, and body, and I yield unto thee all my hope and conſolation, all my diſtreſſes, and my miſeries, my life, and the end thereof, that by thy moſt holy merits, and interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all my works may be directed, and diſpoſed according to thine, and thy Sons will? if we may place our hope and confidence in the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> in all our afflictions, both in life, and death, what could we do more on <hi>Chriſt?</hi> or how could they expreſs
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49882:81"/> greater affiance on Chriſt, than they do here of the Virgin? or in what fuller terms can they reſigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p themſelves to their Saviour; than they uſe here to her, when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves to her, that by her merits and interceſſion all their workes may be directed according to her's, and her ſons will? where then the Creature is drawn off from his intire confidence on Chriſt, and perſwaded to leane on a fellow creature, that muſt be abſur'd and impious, but it is ſo in theſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the <hi>titles</hi> they aſcribe to her, and the <hi>Prayſes</hi> they give her: I do not ſpeak of thoſe flattering ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which ſome ſuperſtitious perſons have uſed, as <hi>Bernadinus Senenſis &amp; Bernardinus de Buſtis:</hi> of whom the former faies <note n="*" place="margin">Berna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enens. <hi>Serm 61. Art. 1. c.</hi> 11.</note>. That the Bleſſed Virgin did more for God, or at leaſt as much as he did unto all mankind, and for our comfort we may ſay that in reſpect of the Bleſſed Virgin God himſelf is after a
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49882:81"/> ſort more bound to us, than we to him. The other ſaies <note n="*" place="margin">Bern. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bustis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riale part. 6. Serm. 2. memb.</hi> 3.</note> that though the Virgin ſang, he that is mighty hath done great things to me, yet he du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſay, thou haſt done grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things to him who is mighty. Theſe I will not charge on them, which may ſeem rather the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies of private fancies, than any allowed expreſſions, yet if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult their publick Offices, we ſhall ſee thoſe things aſcribed to her, which are abſur'd, and unfit to be aſcribed to any Creature: to call her the <hi>Star</hi> of the Sea which ſeeming like ſome title the <hi>Poets</hi> gave to <hi>Venus,</hi> may paſs by a <hi>Poetical</hi> licence, but to call her <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Mercy, Queen</hi> of <hi>Heaven, Lady</hi> of <hi>Angels, Empreſs</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Offic. <hi>B. Mariae</hi> ad Laudes Festo. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rif. Him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ave Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note>. Theſe we think are groundleſs Titles, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avour rather of a luxuriant wit, than any true piety: for though ſhe is bleſſed among women, yet we do not find her exalted above Angels: though ſhe was full of grace, yet here's no reaſon to call her mother of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49882:82"/> grace: though ſhe be exalted into glory, yet why muſt ſhe be cal'd <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Heaven?</hi> why do they pray Queen of Angels bring us into the kingdom of Heaven? as it is in the <hi>Breviary</hi> of <hi>York</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Infra Octa Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpt. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar. 6.</hi> die Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed. commun.</note>: why do they ſing in the Office of the Virgin on the Purification?
<q>
                  <l>Hayle <hi>Queen</hi> the Heavenly armies guiding.</l>
                  <l>Hayle <hi>Lady</hi> over Angels biding.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Enough of this is to be had in the <hi>Salisbury</hi> Miſſal, as that God hath <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſ. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Fest. B. <hi>Mar.</hi> poſt orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am.</note> done mercifully with us, ſince he hath appointed his mother to be our <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate</hi> in Heaven, and in the Sequence ſung on the Feaſt of the Conception, that ſhe is the mother of Orphans, the eaſe of the oppreſſed, the help of the weak, and they add <hi>omnibus es omnia:</hi> now what ground to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe theſe ſuperlative honours to her? what aſſurance that theſe are not unwarrantable Titles? but they go further, and tell us, the rever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49882:82"/> they ſhew to the mother, is given to the Son, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o. with their whole deſires, and voices, they inſiſt on her praiſes, and ſay that ſhe in the bearing of her Son did deſtroy <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum diabolicae ſeditionis Chirogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum,</hi> the ancient hand writing of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh ſedition, and opened the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven to believers <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Breviar</hi> Ebor. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem.</hi> B. Mar. <hi>Lect.</hi> 1.</note>. There is a prayer to the B. Virgin, in which they call her Fountain of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Fountain of health and grace, Fountaine of comfort and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, Fountain of piety and joy, Fountain of life and pardon <note n="†" place="margin">Offic. <hi>B. Mar.</hi> inter orationes.</note>: If they aſcribe to her theſe Titles, then they give to the Creature, what is due to the Creator, God bleſſed for ever; how can they call her Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of grace? when it is the honour of Chriſt, that <hi>of his fullneſs we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive grace for grace</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. 16.</note>; <hi>and in him all fullneſs dwels</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. 19.</note>: or how is ſhe the Fountain of life, when 'tis Chriſts pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar houour to have life in him <note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 11.</note>, <hi>and our life is hid in Chriſt;</hi> or how can ſhe be the Fountain of pardon?
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49882:83"/> when through Chriſt alone we have remiſſion of ſins by his blood. Or how can they ſing that redundancy of grace is given to the Virgin, whereby all things are fragrant and acceptable to God. <hi>O nimia redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gratiae datae Virgini, quâ cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſunt fragrantia, &amp; grata ſummo numini</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Aeterni Patris. in Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> B. Mar. <hi>Paris apud Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Gourſette.</hi> 155<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, when 'tis by Chriſt alone we are made acceptable to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: This is the ſum of this firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that in the Offices of the Virgin there are many prayers unfit to offer to any Creature, and many Titles aſcribed to her, which are groundleſs, abſur'd, and derogating from the honour of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I inſtance in the abſur'd expreſſions which they uſe to the Croſs for they direct their prayers not only to Chriſt crucified, but (if there be any ſenſe in the expreſſions) to the material Croſs ſo in the Office of the Croſs, they ſay, <hi>O venerable Croſs which haſt brought Salvation to wretches, with what praiſes ſhall</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Office of the Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs at Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh.</note>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:49882:83"/> 
               <hi>I extoll thee? for thou haſt prepared unto us the Heavenly life?</hi> at the <hi>Prime they ſay, O Admirable lignum, in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſti curiâ fac nos cantare triumphum.</hi> O Admirable wood, cauſe us to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the heavenly Court: now this is abſur'd to aſcribe that to the Croſs, which is onely due to Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who by his ſufferings on the Croſs purchaſed Salvation for us, or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our prayers and praiſes to that which was only an <hi>inanimate</hi> Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts ſufferings: but if theſe expreſſions do not ſeem ſtrange, there is worſe behind. At the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of the Invention of the Croſs they ſing <note n="*" place="margin">Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>viar. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bor.</hi> Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Invent. Sancta Crucis.</note>, <hi>O Crux ſplendidor cunctis aſtris, mundo celebris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anctior univerſis,</hi> &amp;c. O Croſs more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than all the Stars, famous in the world, holyer than all things, which waſt only worthy to bear the price of the world: <hi>Salva praeſentem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervam laudibus tuis congregatam</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. <hi>Roman.</hi> in Festo In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. &amp; Exalt. Crucis.</note>. Save this preſent company aſſembled for thy prayſes: but how the Croſs ſhould be holyer than all things, how
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49882:84"/> it could be call'd worthy to bear Chriſt; I underſtand not: what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency was there in that wood, which made it worthy to bear our Saviour? what worthy ſtock was it choſen from to touch his holy parts? as they ſing in the Himn <hi>Vixil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> *: or by what propriety, and <note place="margin">† <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione inter Himnos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi> 1552.</note> congruity of ſpeech can they direct their prayers to that material wood to ſave them, who were met to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate its prayſes? much like ſtuff if not worſe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mains behind in that Himn, <hi>O Crux ave ſpes, unica hoc paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis tempore, auge piis juſtitiam, reiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que dona veniam</hi> *: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayle O Croſs <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Breviar.</hi> Rom. <hi>Feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Sanct. Crucis.</hi>
               </note> our onely hope in this paſſion time, increa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e righteouſneſs to the godly, and give pardon to the guilty; but how can they ſay the wooden Croſs is their only hope? how can they beg righteouſneſs and pardon from it? if they tell us theſe are lofty <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of pious wits, I muſt ſtill wonder how their Church can allow ſuch roving humors among their ſerious d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>votions; or how theſe expreſſions
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49882:84"/> which are deſigned for the praiſes of of the wooden Croſs can by any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable congruity be underſtood of Chriſt; or if they be diſallowed that yet they ſhould be retained in the <hi>Breviaries</hi> reformed by <hi>Pius</hi> 5. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe we have in the Breviary of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> on the <hi>Feaſt</hi> of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Croſs, <hi>Ara Crucis, Lampas lucis, vera ſalus hominum, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis pronum fac patronum quem tuliſti Dominum:</hi> where they intreat the wooden Croſs to make Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to them. Such kind of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they have in their private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, as to our Ladies girdle, <hi>O veneranda Zona fac nos haeredes vitae Aeternae, &amp; ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c vitam ab interitu conſerva, habeamus te vires &amp; auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, murum &amp; propugnaculum,</hi> &amp;c. O bleſſed girdle make us the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of eternal life, keep our preſent life from deſtruction, O unſpotted girdle of the unſpotted Virgin ſave thine inheritance, be thou our ſtrength and help, our wall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, our heaven and refuge: ſuch
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49882:85"/> alſo is the prayer to <hi>Veronica</hi> or the Picture of our Saviours bloody face on a napkin. <hi>Salve vultns Domini imago beata, ex aeterno munere mire decorata lumen funde cordibus ex vi tibi datâ; &amp; à noſtris ſenſibus tolle colligata,</hi> &amp;c. here they pray that by the virtue given to that Picture it would infuſe light into their hearts: and they conclude, <hi>nos deduc ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria O foelix figura, ad videndum faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em quae eſt Chriſti pura,</hi> O happy fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure bring us to ſee the pure face of Chriſt: but what ground to hope for theſe bleſſings from inſenſible things? or to pray to them for theſe ends? or what aſſurance is there that ſuch virtue is imprinted in them? and if there be no ground for ſuch expreſſions, then they are unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable and abſur'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I inſtance in their moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred office of the maſs, this them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſs was anciently corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and many things crept in (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through the fault of times or
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49882:85"/> mens negligence or wickednes) were far from the dignity of ſuch a Sacrifice: <note n="*" place="margin">Cone. <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> Seſ. 22. Decr. de o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. &amp; evit. in Cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. Miſſ.</note> and ꝑo. the council re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſuch things to be taken away, which either Covetouſnes or irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, or ſuperſtition had brought in: accordingly the Miſſal was corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by <hi>Pius</hi> the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and after another review publiſht by <hi>Clement</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> which is the Authentick Miſſal at this day, now in this I obſerve many things abſurd, vain, or untrue I mention not the multitude of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which clog the ſervice diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Prieſts thoughts, and reduce the ſimplicity of Chriſtianity to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Paedagogy: as in the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Croſſing themſelves, in the very canon of the Maſſe the Prieſt is enjoyned to make 25 Croſſes at ſeveral times, beſides the ſigning himſelf with the <hi>Patten</hi> from the forehead to the Breſt, and with part of the hoſt he muſt make the ſigne of the Croſſe thrice on the <hi>Chalice:</hi> as litle reaſon can be given for the <hi>Pax</hi> which muſt be given only to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49882:86"/> Magiſttrates and noble perſons <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Carem. Epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>op l. 1. c</hi> 24.</note>, or to be moſt eminent as <hi>Gavantus</hi> ſaies <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it.</hi> 10.</note>, unleſs it were no matter to have Peace with the Poor, provided they could have it with the rich, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſo for the Preiſts murmuring the words of Conſecration, and when he places the Chalice on the Corporal for his ſaying with a low voice, <hi>as oft as ye do this do it in remembrace of me,</hi> and in the Cloſe of the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> ſpeaking low, <hi>Amen:</hi> of theſe things they give ſo little reaſon that we may, with greater, judg them the fruit only of ignorance and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: I ſhall ſpeake only of the Prayers themſelves. <hi>Firſt,</hi> After the <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertory,</hi> when the Prieſt offers the wafer which he muſt afterward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate, he ſaies, <hi>Suſcipe ſancte pater hanc immaculatam hoſtiam, quam offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro tibi deo vivo pro innumerabilibus peccat is &amp; offenſionibus meis</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Miſſal <hi>Rom. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris 1631</hi> Ordo. Miſſae</note>, receive Holy Father this immaculate hoſt, which I thy unworthy ſervant offer to thee the true and living God for my innumerable ſins, offences and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49882:86"/> negligences, &amp;c. now I ask what they mean by this immaculate hoſt which they offer for ſin? either they mean the wafer, or the real body of Chriſt: they cannot mean this latter for the body is not under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> till after conſecration, and the conſecration (they ſay) is not till theſe words <hi>(hoc est enim corpus meum)</hi> be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and ꝑo. they cannot now offer the body, if they mean the wafer, then they offer to God bread for their ſins, which themſelves will confeſs is abſurd. <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is a Prayer which begins <hi>Suſcipe San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Trinitas, &amp;c.</hi> And in this the Prieſt ſaies, he offers this oblation for the memory of our Saviours Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Reſurrection and Aſſention, and in the honour of the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <hi>Peter and Paul</hi> that it may profit them for their Honour, and us for our Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vation: now of what doth the Prayer mean? take it either of the Elements or of Chriſts body yet I underſtand not how they can offer
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49882:87"/> for the Saints honour; how they can intreat God to receive Chriſts body in honour of his Saints; how an immediate act of adoration to God can be ſaid to be profitable for their Saints honour; or if it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to increaſe their glory, how it can ſtand with their own <hi>tenents,</hi> that it is impious to pray for a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> when yet they pray for St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul, ut iis proficiat ad honorem,</hi> but of this more afterwards. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> After the Conſecration it is ſaid, we offer unto thy excellent majeſty of thy own gifts, a pure Hoſt, a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hoſt, the holy bread of Eternal life, and the Cup of Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>ſuper quae propitio ac ſereno vultu reſpicere digneris,</hi> upon which things vouchſafe to look with a propitious and ſerene countenance, &amp;c. Now this is abſur'd, that we ſhould pray that God would look propitiouſly on his own Son in whom he is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies well pleaſed: or that God would accept this Sacrifice of Chriſt, when it is that ſweet ſmelling Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49882:87"/> which God allwaies doth accept. Indeed <hi>Bellarmine</hi> gives us an excuſe for the harſhneſs of theſe words, and faies, the offering in reſpect of the thing offered, and of Chriſt the principal offerer, alwaies pleaſes God, yet in reſpect of the miniſter or people who offer with him it may not pleaſe God, and ꝑo. they pray that God would look propitiouſly on this gift as it is offered by them: but this evaſion will not ſerve, for they tell us, that the value of this Sacrifice is not <hi>ex opere operantis,</hi> from the condition or worth of the miniſter, but <hi>ex opere operato</hi> from the nature of the thing it ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is done as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell.</hi> l. 2. c. 4. de Miſſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cundo.</note>, and ꝑo. it pleaſes God though he who offer it do not pleaſe him <note n="†" place="margin">§ terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um est.</note>; ſo that ſince the value of the Sacrifice is wholly from the thing that is offered, ꝑo. as it is offered by us or not, offered by us doth no way alter the acceptableneſs of it to God, but ſtill the prayer muſt remain ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, for they pray that God would
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49882:88"/> look propitiouſly on the body and blood of Chriſt, and accept them, when God allwaies doth accept them, and can never be diſpleaſed with them. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is a fourth prayer, which begins <hi>ſupplices rogamus,</hi> &amp;c. There they pray, that God would command theſe things to be carried by his holy Angels unto the high Altar in the ſight of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, &amp;c. Now what are theſe things? if they ſay, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the faithfull; that cannot be meant, for this prayer is to the thing ſpoken of in the former prayer, and that was the body and blood of Chriſt, the holy bread of Eternal life, and the Cup of everlaſting Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; if they ſay that they are the body and blood of Chriſt (as it is plain from the words that they are) then theſe have been long ſince in Heaven, and Chriſt lives there to make interceſſion for us, how then can they be carried up into Heaven? and ꝑo. he fixes another ſenſe <note n="*" place="margin">l. 2. de Miſſa. c. 24. Sect. reſpond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, that thoſe expreſſions muſt be underſtood
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49882:88"/> ſpiritually, and ſignifie only this, that the Angels by their prayers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend our obedience to God; but ſtill he forgets, that the things here in the prayer are not our obedience, and ſervice, but the body and blood of Chriſt: that there is no mention of our obedience and ſervice in that prayer, but both this and the former prayer are connected with thoſe words, we offer to thee a pure Hoſt, an holy Hoſt, an undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Hoſt, the holy bread of Eternal life, and the Cup of everlaſting Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: for they ſubjoyne in the next words, <hi>upon which things vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to look propitiouſly,</hi> &amp;c. and then follows this prayer, <hi>we humbly beſeech thee, command theſe things to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,</hi> &amp;c. it muſt then be meant of his body and blood; but how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable is it to deſire the Angels may commend the Sacrifice of Chriſt with their prayers? or that their prayers ſhould aſſiſt to render the Sacrifice of Chriſt acceptable? as if any thing ſhould add any worth to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49882:89"/> Chriſts Sacrifice: but if this will not remove the incongruities of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Durand</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rational. Div. Offic. l. 4. c. 44. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. E.</note> tells us, <hi>tantae profunditatis ſunt haec verba, ut intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus humanus vix ea ſufficiat pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare:</hi> Theſe are ſuch profound ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that humane underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can hardly pierce into them: well ſaid, a good excuſe for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe; to call it a profound expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to condemn the weakneſs of our underſtandings when 'tis the abſurdity of their words: theſe are fine things to pleaſe them, who are wont to admire every thing in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; like thoſe Courtiers which cry up the Princes ſtammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a grace in his ſpeech: a ſtrange thing, that thoſe expreſſions muſt paſs for moſt Divine, which have leaſt reaſon, and ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Thus I have inſtanced in ſeveral abſurdities, untruths and impieties in the Offices of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, which juſtifie my third argument, That it is unreaſonable to be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to believe that to be the pureſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49882:89"/> Church whoſe publique Offices are very corrupt, but the Offices of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church are ſo, ꝑo.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <p>MY fourth <hi>Conſideration</hi> ſhall be drawn from the Irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able oppoſition of their prayers to their publique <hi>Doctrine:</hi> very many prayers which are contrary to their preſent Innovations are expunged, and many prayers yet retained can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be reconciled with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Doctrine, ꝑo. we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to adhere to the preſent <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Many prayers which were contrary to their preſent innovations are expunged, this is not only our complaint, but of one that lived, and died in the <hi>Roman</hi> communion <hi>Johannes Marſillius</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Defeſadis Gio. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio. Della</hi> 4. <hi>prop. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Card<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aies, it is a thing known by all, that in the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49882:90"/> books of <hi>Councels,</hi> of <hi>Canons,</hi> and of the <hi>Doctors,</hi> yea in the <hi>Breviaries</hi> and <hi>Miſſals</hi> thoſe places, are expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, which ſpeak in favour of the <hi>Laity,</hi> that they might ſee if they could eſtabliſh from Antiquity, the opinion of the Popes illimited power in temporals; ſo that he who compares the Books Printed in 1530 and 1550, and thoſe at preſent <hi>(i)</hi> at the time of the interdict of <hi>Venice,</hi> will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that we have found after ſuch a vintage any gleanings in defence of our Prince: and ꝑo. firſt I will give you his Inſtance in the prayer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St. <hi>Paul June</hi> 30. where it was anciently ſaid, qui <hi>B. Petro animas, ligandi &amp; ſolvendi pontificium dediſti,</hi> this he ſaies, he ſaw in Breviaries which had been written above 200 yeares, and which had been printed about an hundred, and yet the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the <hi>Roman</hi> breviary have left out the word <hi>[animas]:</hi> will you ſee <hi>Bellarmines</hi> anſwer? in his reply to <hi>Marſillius</hi> he ſaies <hi>forſi la divina pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49882:90"/> ha inſpirato li reformatori, &amp;c.</hi> Perhaps the Divine Providence hath inſpired the reformers to take it away? but why muſt it be taken away; becauſe (as <hi>Marſilius</hi> ſtates the caſe) the Pope, deſigning the advancement of his Power that he might Challinge as St <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor a power in temporals, ſaw that this reſtriction was no way conſiſtent with his deſign; for if the binding and looſing be properly of Souls, it muſt be a meerly Spiritual Power, and ſo no way conſiſtent with that ſupereminent power in temporals, which the Pope and his Courtiers claimed: a good reaſon then to take this away, and a fine excuſe to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie it: Gods providence muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire theſe reformers ſuch an inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion indeed as the <hi>Trent</hi> Fathers had, when if we believe the Proverb, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt came from</hi> Rome <hi>in a cloke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bag: Secondly,</hi> I will give that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>De. Rep. Eccles.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 164.</note> had obſerved in <hi>Bertram's</hi> book, when <hi>Bertram</hi> would prove
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49882:91"/> that the bread and wine are figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively the body and blood of Chriſt, and though they are call'd the body and blood of Chriſt, yet there are ſuch things ſaid of them which are Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated by the Church in a miſtery, as cannot be ſaid according to that manner they are known to exiſt, and ꝑo. they muſt be underſtood to be the body and blood of Chriſt in a figure, he proves this by two prayers in the Miſſal, which were ſaid after the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, the firſt is, <hi>Pignus aeternae vitae capientes humiliter imploramus, ut quod imagine contingimus Sacramenti mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtâ participatione ſumamus:</hi> taking the pledg of eternal life we humbly beſeech, that what we touch in the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of the Sacrament we may alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by manifeſt participation: from hence <hi>Bertram</hi> gather'd, that a pledge, and an Image only ſignifying the things which they belong to, but not manifeſtly ſhewing them, ꝑo. that which is now made in the Sacrament is different from that which ſhall be afterwards manifeſted, ꝑo. that which
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49882:91"/> the Church Celebrates is the body and blood of Chriſt, but yet as a pledge, as an Image, and when there is no more pledge or Image the truth it ſelf, <hi>(i. e)</hi> the body of Chriſt will apear: now this Prayer is not to be found in the Miſſal ſaies <hi>Sſpalato.</hi> Another he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Per ficiant in nobis Domine quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, tua Sacramenta quod continent, ut quae nunc ſpecie geramus rei veritate capiamus:</hi> let thy Sacraments O Lord effects in us what they contain, that what we now hold in ſhew, we may receive in truth; from this he argues, there being a difference betwixt <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> and <hi>veritas (i. e)</hi> betwixt what is in ſhew, and what is according to it's true nature ꝑo. that body &amp; blood of Chriſt which is here held by the Church differs from that which ſhall be glorified in the reſurrection: this prayer is clipt ſaies <hi>Spalato,</hi> &amp; inſtead of <hi>ſpecie</hi> they read <hi>ſpe,</hi> (yet ſince that is oppoſed to truth in this place, it ſhews that we do not receive that which is truly the body of Chriſt according to its proper nature) and ſo it was read
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49882:92"/> in their reformed Miſſals, in <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates Liturgicae</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sabbato</hi> 4. <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum per Balthas. Beller.</hi> 1605.</note>, printed at <hi>Doway</hi> 1605. which the author ſaies he took <hi>à capite ad calcem</hi> out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Miſal, the prayer runs, <hi>ut quae nunc ſpe geramus,</hi> &amp;c. but I wave this latter, for the word <hi>[ſpecie]</hi> is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in the <hi>Paris</hi> edition of the Miſſal 1631. Many more alterations in their Offices might be produced, which will evidence the innovations in the Doctrine of their Church, and which (I hope) will be effected by by ſome induſtrious perſon, who hath the opportunity of variety of choice Miſſals and Breviaries, and their other books of devotion, whereby to diſcover thoſe alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their preſent from their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Offices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I will rather inſtance in thoſe paſſages yet retained, and are not reconcileable with the grounds of their preſent <hi>Doctrine:</hi> As, <hi>Firſt,</hi> I inſtance in the private Maſſes, when the Prieſt communicates alone; for many are bound by the Statutes
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49882:92"/> of their foundation as the <hi>Chantry</hi> Prieſts to ſay Maſs for the Souls of their founders, many perſons for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, ſome by agreement (and the higheſt ordinary rate in theſe Countries, ſaies <hi>Fitz-Simon</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Of the Maſs 1 book 2 part 12 chapt.</note>, is a ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) ſay a Maſs, and ꝑo. whether there be any to Communicate or no, yea though but one to anſwer the Prieſt, and ſometime none <note n="†" place="margin">Gavant. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>tit.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 1.</note>, yet he ſaies Maſs: and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> though it wiſhes all who ſtand by would not only communicate by ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual affection, but Sacramental participation of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> yet it doth not condemn thoſe <hi>Maſſes,</hi> in which the Prieſt communicates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but approves them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them: now the prayers and rules of the Maſs are no way recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable with this Doctrine, and practice: for, <hi>Firſt,</hi> If there be none to communicate, how can the Prieſt uſe this exhortation which is in the <hi>Ordo Miſſae</hi> after the prayer <hi>ſuſcipe Sancta Trinitas? Orate fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres ut meum ac veſtrum ſacrificium
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49882:93"/> fit acceptabile,</hi> &amp;c. pray bretheren that my Sacrifice and yours may be acceptable: <hi>this exhortation</hi> (ſaies the <hi>Rubrick) muſt be ſaid by the Prieſt with his voice toward the people; and his Tone a little raiſed,</hi> and in their private Maſs all this is done, though there be none preſent: the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſuppoſes ſome communicating or at leaſt ſome preſent, why muſt he ſay <hi>Brethren,</hi> if he ſuppoſes there needs be none, or at leaſt but one? why ſhould he <hi>raiſe his voice,</hi> when he can expect none to anſwer, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the ſtones ſay <hi>Amen?</hi> why muſt he <hi>turne to the people</hi> if it ſuppoſe a Maſs where there are none, or but one preſent? <hi>Laſtly,</hi> why muſt he ſay <hi>my Sacrifice and yours,</hi> if it did not ſuppoſe ſome joyning in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice? <hi>Secondly,</hi> I inſtance in that exhortation, <hi>lift up your hearts</hi> with the <hi>reſponſe, habemus ad dominum:</hi> if we lift them up to the Lord, &amp;c. ſo the Prieſt ſaies <hi>dominus vobiſcum,</hi> the Lord be with you, the anſwer is, <hi>and with thy Spirit,</hi> now if in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49882:93"/> the framing this Office, it were not ſuppoſed that others were preſent to whom the Prieſt might direct the exhortation, and that they ſhould return the anſwer it had been fooliſh to have appointed the uſe of theſe words: for its altogether vain, and rediculous to ſay, <hi>lift up your hearts</hi> when there is none to hear him, or to ſay, <hi>let us pray,</hi> when he prayes by himſelf, or <hi>the Lord be with you,</hi> when he ſpeaks to the bare walls. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I inſtance in the <hi>commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio pro vivis,</hi> where the Prieſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires God <hi>to remember all thoſe that ſtand by, whoſe faith and devotion are known to thee, for whom we offer, or who offer to thee this Sacrifice of praiſe,</hi> &amp;c. Now this expreſſion ſuppoſes there muſt be ſome that ſtand by, or elſe the Prieſt ſhould be bound ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly to pray for them that ſtand by, when there are none at all. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I inſtance in the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Supplices te rogamus,</hi> &amp;c. there he prayes <hi>that as many of us as receive the body and blood of thy Son from
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49882:94"/> this participation of the Altar may be filled with all Heavenly Benedictions and Grace:</hi> here the Prayer ſuppoſes ſome receiving, or if there be none to receive with the Prieſt, how can he ſay <hi>that as many of us as receive,</hi> &amp;c? <hi>Bellarmin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>de Miſſa. c.</hi> 10. <hi>reſp. ad object.</hi> 10.</note> thinks to ſolve this ſcruple by telling us, that theſe words are uſed for thoſe who communicate at preſent, and if there be none then it muſt refer to thoſe who are abſent, who communicate elſewhere: but this will not ſerve, for the Prayer refers to thoſe who communicate here and not elſewhere: for elſe how can it ſay <hi>as many of us?</hi> and <hi>as many as receive from this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the Altar?</hi> for the words <hi>[this participation] ex hac altaris participatione,</hi> reſtrain it to thoſe who are now to receive. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I inſtance in the prayer after the Prieſt hath received, <hi>quod ore ſumpſimus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>what we have O Lord taken with our mouthes, let us allſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with a pure mind,</hi> &amp;c. Now how can they ſay this, unleſs they
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:49882:94"/> ſuppoſe ſome receiving? for if they only Communicate ſpiritually, as the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſaies, aſſiſting with their prayers, then they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to receive it with their mouthes, beſides he deſires <hi>that what they have received with their mouthes, they may receive with a pure minde.</hi> And ꝑo. this receiving doth ſuppoſe that former receiving: ſo that we may from hence judge this to have been the Primitive inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that ſome ſhould Communicate with the Prieſt, and that as <hi>Walafrid Strabo</hi> ſaies, <hi>it was only a lawfull Maſs, in which there was the Prieſt, thoſe that anſwer, and thoſe who offer, and communicate; ſicut ipſa compoſitio precum evidenti ratione demonſtrat,</hi> as the frame of the prayers (ſaies he) evidently ſhews: and I add (as I have now inſtanced) that the expreſſions yet retained are contrary to their preſent Practice, and Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I inſtance in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>merit,</hi> in this indeed I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49882:95"/> ſee much difference betwixt the moderate <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and us, as <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">De Rep. Eccleſ. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. c. 7. u. 8.</note> and <hi>Forbes</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">Conſid. Modest a. l. 5. c. 4.</note> obſerve, for they will tell us, <hi>that they account good works meritorious, not for the value, and worth of the work it ſelf: but from Gods acceptation, promiſe, and appointment,</hi> and ſo <hi>Caſſander</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conſult. ad Art. 6. de operibus bonis.</note> ſaies, that the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> and other <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks</hi> did not differ from this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for they placed the force of the merit of their righteouſneſs, in Gods free acceptation, and liberal promiſe, and that their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs what ever it was, was Gods gift, and due by right of ſervice to him, &amp;c. yet if we conſult the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and rigid writers among the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> they will tell us, <hi>that our works do merit from the dignity of the work:</hi> ſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaies <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>De Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stif. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note>, <hi>that it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis &amp; veriſſima Theologorum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia,</hi> that there is a <hi>meritum de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digno, that there is a ſtrict equallity betwixt the worth of the work it ſelf, and the reward:</hi> and from <hi>Vaſquez</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 1 <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundae. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Q.</hi> 114. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 214. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 5.</note> we have this aſſertion <hi>that good works
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49882:95"/> of juſt perſons are of themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any covenant or acception worthy of the reward of Eternal life, and have an equall value of condignity to the attaining Eternall glory.</hi> This opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they think is backt by the Council which <hi>Anathematizes</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 6. <hi>Can.</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>them, who deny that good works done by the grace of God, and merit of Chriſt, do truly deſerve increaſe of grace and Eternall glory:</hi> and the intereſt of this opinion hath ſo far prevailed, that whereas in the <hi>ordo baptizandi cum modo viſitandi,</hi> &amp;c. Printed at <hi>Venice</hi> 1575, there was this queſtion propoſed to the dying man, <hi>Credis non propriis meritis, ſed paſſionis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti virtute &amp; merito ad gloriam pervenire?</hi> doſt thou believe that thou ſhalt come to glory not by thy own merits, but by the virtue and merit of Jeſus Chriſts paſſion? and this was alſo propoſed to him, doſt thou believe that Jeſus Chriſt died for our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that none can be ſaved by his own merits, or by any other
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49882:96"/> means, but by the merits of his paſſion? both theſe are commanded to be expunged by the <hi>Index expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorius</hi> of Card. <hi>Quiroga</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Index. Expurg. per Card.</hi> Quirog. Madrit. 1584. <hi>&amp; recuſ.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noviae. 1611.</note> 1584. and alſo by that of Cardinal <hi>Sando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</hi> 1612. This expreſſion is alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged out of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> Annotations, in the firſt Chapter of St. <hi>Luke</hi> on theſe words <hi>they ſhall call me bleſſed;</hi> Then Gods name is glorified when nothing is aſcribed to our own merits, but the whole to Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: this Doctrine of merit though diſliked by the moderate ſort, and hardly owned where they converſe with <hi>Proteſtants</hi> is yet ſtifly maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the common opinion in thoſe Countries which are intirely <hi>Popiſh,</hi> ſeems to be countenanced by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Council, and more fully by thoſe who have been imployed in purging <hi>Heretical</hi> books, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, the prayers which may be found in the Offices are no way reconcileable with it; for though in their diſputes with men, they pretend the merit of their
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49882:96"/> works, yet in their Prayers to God they fly to his ſole mercy: ſo they ſing <note n="*" place="margin">In dedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sancti Mich. Archang. ad veſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras in Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Christe.</note> 
               <hi>mundo corde, corpore Paradiſo redde tuo nos ſolâ clementiâ:</hi> bring us by thy alone mercy to thy Paradiſe with clean heart, and body: and in the Prayer which begins <hi>nobis qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> in the Canon of the Maſs, they beg, that God would bring them into the ſociety of Saints, <hi>non aeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator meriti, ſed veniae largitor,</hi> not eſteeming their merits, but pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their offences: if there could be any exact merit, which from its own dignity deſerves glory, why do they then fly to his ſole mercy? and if the whole be not aſcribed to Gods mercy, but mans merits, why do they beg that God would not weigh their merits but pardon their offences?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I inſtance in the Doctrine of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> with their Prayers for the dead, the Doctrine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> is, <hi>that the Souls in Purgatory are helped by the Suffrages of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:49882:97"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc.</hi> Trident. <hi>Seſs.</hi> 25.</note>, for after Death thoſe Souls which have not been throughly purged, in this life are carried into a place of torment, where they are detained till hey are throughly purged, <note place="margin">† <hi>S. C. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Dr.</hi> Pierce. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 12.</note> and then are carried into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and ꝑo. they pray for thoſe <hi>that God will forgive their ſins and aſſwage their ſufferings*,</hi> &amp;c. for thoſe who are very good they give thanks, but for thoſe who are in this middle eſtate they pray for pardon and Mercy, and that not only on the day of their Buriall, but alſo alſo the on third, on the ſeventh, on the thirtieth, and on the <hi>anniverſary</hi> of their death they ſay Maſs for their Souls, and by this hope to rid them quickly out of Purgatory: now the Prayers they uſe are irreconciliable with this Doctrine. For <hi>Firſt,</hi> there are Prayers for thoſe whom they believe to be in Heaven, even for the greateſt Saints: this <hi>S. C.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſwer to Dr.</hi> Pierce <hi>c.</hi> 10 <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes was anciently ſo, but then they were not ſuch Prayers as were Made for the imperfect <hi>(i)</hi> for remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49882:97"/> of ſins refreſhment, &amp;c. but for acceſſion of glory to Saints already glorified, but there is more than ſo: for they uſe the ſame requeſt for thoſe, who (they ſay) are in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and for thoſe we all believe to be in glory: they pray for all that reſt in Chriſt, that God would give them a place of refreſhment, light, and peace <note n="*" place="margin">Commem. pro. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct. in Can. Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</note>; now if the Saints reſt in Chriſt then they are included in this Prayer, and they beg for the Saints who are glorified refreſhment and peace, which is the requeſt, <hi>(S. C.</hi> Saies) that is to be made for imperfect <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And wee find ſuch a prayer, that God by whoſe mercy the Soul's of the faithfull reſt, would grant to all thy ſervants here and every where reſting in Chriſt, pardon of ſin, that being abſolved from all guilt, they may reſt with <note place="margin">† In cratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus pro his qui in Caemit. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſe.</note> thee for ever*: and there was a prayer for St. <hi>Leo, ut per haec placa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis officia illum beata retributio comitetur</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In festo Sancti <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis</hi> ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſecreta.</note>, that by theſe offices of atonement a bleſſed retribution may accompany him: what do theſe
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49882:98"/> words ſignefie? not an increaſe of glory, but ſimply that he may have glory, not an addition of happines but ſimply that a bleſſed reward may accompany him: and how can the Sacrifice they offer here be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to be a thanksgiven for Leo, (as it muſt be for thoſe who are very good) when it's call'd an office of atonement <hi>Secondly,</hi> there are no prayers in their publique offices for deliverance from <hi>Purgatory</hi> that they may be quickly eaſed of their paines, and delivered from torments, and if there be no prayer for ſpeedy eaſe of thoſe pains, and quick riddance from them, then their prayers are not ſuitable to their Doctrine. The Prayers are either <hi>Firſt</hi> to prevent falling into puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhment; ſo in the office of buriall, they Pray that God would receive the ſoul returning to him, and cloath it with an Heavenly Garment, and waſh it with the holy fountain of eternal life: and in the next Prayer, they Pray <note n="*" place="margin">in offic. Sepult. O atio: ſuſcipe domine.</note> that God would receive the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oul of his ſervant, which he
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49882:98"/> hath called from the priſon of the body, and free it from the Princes of darknes, and the places of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that being delivered from the bond of his ſins he may obtain the bleſſing of eternal reſt, and light: and this <hi>Antiphona</hi> is ſung, when the body is caried to the Church <note n="*" place="margin">Offic. ſepult An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiph. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venite.</note> 
               <hi>help O ye Saints, meet him O ye Angils of the Lord receiving his Soule, and offering it in the ſight of the higheſt: let Chriſt receive thee who cal'd thee, and carry thee into Abrahams boſome:</hi> and ſo in the prayer, <hi>O God to whom all things do live,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat that God would command the Soul of his Servant to be received by the hands of his holy Angels, and to be carried into the boſome of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs:</hi> and in the prayer <hi>fac quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that he may not receive any recompence of his actions in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, who hath in his deſires kept thy will:</hi> I'le inſtance in one prayer more: <hi>Deus origo pietatis,</hi> &amp;c. where they deſire, that the Soul may indure no treacheries of the devil meeting him, that God would
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49882:99"/> free him from the infernall Gulfe, and deliver him from the cruel bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of a hot Hell, placing it in the pleaſure of Paradiſe: <hi>Let it not feel O mercifull Father the heat of the flames, the anguiſh of puniſhments, or the horror of darkneſs, but being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by thy bounty may obtain to eſcape the Judgment of revenge.</hi> Now theſe prayers are not reconcileable with their grounds, for 'tis their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that thoſe who dye in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſtate muſt neceſſarily go to that place of purgation; but now in thoſe prayers, they deſire that God would receive the Soul when it comes out of the body, and free it from the <hi>Prince</hi> of darkneſs, and places of puniſhments, and that it may not feel the heat of the flames, but being prevented by Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may eſcape the Judgment of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. They pretend in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that by their prayers they free the Souls from the puniſhments they feel, for they neceſſarily muſt indure puniſhment, but the prayers
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:49882:99"/> themſelves ſpeak of preventing the falling into puniſhment. And ꝑo. theſe prayers cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled with their Doctrine. <hi>Secondly,</hi> there are Prayers, which ſuppoſe the ſoule as yet in it's paſſage, and ꝑo. they deſire, that it may not fall into puniſhment, but God would place it in the land of reſt and light. After the departure of the ſoul out of the body they pray, that God would receive the ſoul returning to him: <hi>let Michael the Angel of the teſtament be preſent with him and vouchſafe by the hands of thy holy Angel to place him in the boſome of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch</hi> Abraham, <hi>that being freed from the Prince of darkneſs, and places of puniſhments, no man may be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with the errors of his nativity or ignorance, &amp;c.</hi> Now though this may ſeem ſutable, when the ſoul is newly gone out of the body, with thoſe, that think there is ſome ſpace of time betwixt the Souls departure, and its receiving its particular doome: but without ſuch a conceit,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49882:100"/> how can they pray at the burial <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Offic. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pult. Orat. Te Domine,</hi> &amp;c.</note>, that God would give his ſervant, whom he cal'd out of the whirlepool of this world a place of refreſhment, and light, that he may paſs by the gates of Hell, and the puniſhments of darkneſs, &amp;c. If at the burial they pray that it may paſs by the gates of Hell, then the Soul is ſtill in its paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: and further they pray, that he may remain in the manſion of the <hi>Saints,</hi> and his ſpirit may receive no hurt: but if his ſpirit was in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then it would receive hurt: ꝑo. by this prayer I underſtand, it is yet in a capacity to receive no hurt, and ꝑo. the Soul muſt yet be in its paſſage: and ſo it is plain from the <hi>Abſolution,</hi> where he ſaies, <hi>the Lord Jeſu Chriſt abſolve thee from all the bond of thy ſins, and I pray thou mayeſt be abſolved before the Tribunal of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> this ſuppoſes, that the Soul is yet in its paſſage to this Tribunal, or why ſhould he pray for this abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before the Tribunal, if he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received the ſentence of that
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49882:100"/> Tribunal? there is another prayer, <hi>that God would receive the Soul of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant freed from Corporal bonds into the peace of his Saints, that being Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into the Region of the living, it may eſcape the place of puniſhment, and the fire of Hell:</hi> all this ſuppoſes that the Soul hath not yet its doome, but is now in its paſſage: and ꝑo. when the body is carrying to the grave, they deſire, <hi>that the Angels would meet him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Soul, and lead him into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and the Martyrs receive him into their aſſembly;</hi> and when the body is laid in the grave, ſtill they pray, <hi>that the Soul being prevented with the gift of thy bounty, it may obain to eſcape the Judgment of revenge</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>In Oratic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Origo pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> &amp;c.</note>. Nor do they end here, but they uſe ſuch expreſſions on the <hi>Trental</hi> and <hi>Anniverſary,</hi> as in the <hi>Offertory, in Anniverſario defuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: free them from the mouth of the Lyon, let not Hell ſwallow them up, let not them fall into the dark place, but let the ſtandard bearer St. Michael bring them into the holy Light,</hi> &amp;c. and the prayers in the <hi>commendatio animarum</hi> which
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:49882:101"/> ſuppoſe the Soul even then in its paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage are uſed at the <hi>Trental</hi> and <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Offic. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pult ſec. uſum. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brica. pag.</hi> 103.</note> but why ſhould thoſe words which commend it in its paſſage be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at theſe times, if they did not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Soul yet in its way? thus theſe prayers contradict their received grounds of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and prayer for the dead, for if the prayers they uſe, ſtill ſuppoſe them in this paſſage, and not come into torment, then they muſt contradict their uſual Doctrine, which concludes them preſently in torment, and that by thoſe prayers they may be ſpeedily delivered from the torment they are in. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> There are other prayers which deſire that the Soul may be freed from Eternal puniſhments, that Hell may not ſwallow them up, and they may not fall into the place of darkneſs <note n="*" place="margin">Miſſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in die ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</note>; and in the firſt prayer at that <hi>Maſs</hi> they pray for <hi>the Soul of thy Servant whom thou haſt commanded this day to depart out of this world, that thou wilt not deliver him into the hand of the enemy, nor forget it finally,</hi> &amp;c. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hoped and believed in thee,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:49882:101"/> that he may not ſuſtain the pains of <hi>Hell,</hi> but poſſeſs joyes everlaſting. This prayer anciently run that he might not ſuſtain <hi>paenas aeternas,</hi> but now this is altered in <hi>poenas inferni,</hi> yet ſtill if they take the word <hi>Hell,</hi> for <hi>Purgatory,</hi> then they pray that God would not ſuffer it to come into Purgatory, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their own Doctrine, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man not throughly purged in this life, muſt be purged in Purgatory. If they underſtand it of the Hell of the damned, and of eternal puniſhments, as there is a Prayer to be uſed at the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> that by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Gods grace he may obtaine to eſcape the Judgment of everlaſting revenge <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> Rom. <hi>l. 1. ſect. 15. c. 1. f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note>, if they underſtand it thus, then I aske, whether they ſuppoſe thoſe perſons for whom they pray are very wicked, or indifferently good: if they be very wicked, then it would be abſurd to pray for their deliverance from everlaſting damnation; for it is certain (ſaies <hi>Bellarmine</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l. 2. de purgatori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c.</hi> 18.</note>) that the Prayers do not profit the damned, for they can not be helped: if they be indifferently good, ſuch as dye in a
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49882:102"/> ſtate of grace though with ſome veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſins, then why do they pray <hi>that he might not fall into Hell?</hi> for this is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready certain: or <hi>that God would not forget them finally, but command them to be received by the holy Angells, and brought into the Country of Paradiſe;</hi> for it is certain, God cannot forget them finally, but the longeſt duration of Purgatory is only till the reſurrection: or why do they pray <hi>that they may not ſuſtain the pains of Hell, but poſſeſs joyes everlaſting, and that they may eſcape E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> revenge?</hi> if their only deſign was to free the Soul from the torments of Purgatory, why is there nothing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe in Purgatory? nothing of quick riddance from thence? (as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend from the apparitions of Souls which have been in Purgatory, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid they were freed by the Maſſes and prayers of the living) yea further, there is one prayer, which refers the pardon of ſin to the reſurrection: in the prayer which begins, <hi>Te Domine Sancte,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">Offic. ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt. ſec. uſum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> they pray, <hi>Let his Spirit receive no hurt, but when the great day of the reſurrection comes, vouchſafe to raiſe him with the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:49882:102"/> Saints and blot out all his offences and ſins even unto the laſt farthing:</hi> now if by the prayers of the living they can procure pardon, then there would not be a farthing to be blotted out at the reſurrection: and ſo this prayer would be uſeleſs All this while we meet with no prayer to put an end to their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to free them quickly from the pains they are now in: they'le tell us indeed, they pray for refreſhment and pardon of ſins, and where muſt they be for whom they pray thus, except in Purgatory? but this doth not follow; for, <hi>Firſt,</hi> There are ancient prayers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, in which they prayed even to give reſt to them, whom they believed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to be in reſt: and therefore this doth not ſuppoſe them in Purgatory: ſo in St. <hi>James</hi> Liturgy (as it is cal'd) he prayes for all from <hi>Abel</hi> the juſt untill this preſent day, that God would give them reſt in the kingdom of heaven: and ſo in <hi>Alcuinus</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Offic. per Ferias. Col. 228. Oper. Edit. <hi>Paris</hi> 1917.</note>, he prayes for the ſpirits of thy ſervants, and handmaids which thou haſt called to thee from the beginning of the world, that thou wouldeſt vouchſafe to give them a
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49882:103"/> lightſome place, a place of refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and eaſe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I gather that they were not in Purgatory, from that commemoration of the dead, which <hi>S. C.</hi> mentions, for thoſe who are gone before us with the ſigne of faith, and repoſe in the ſleep of peace, and reſt in Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, light and peace; for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> ſuppoſe the torments to be greater, than the greateſt torments of this life; now how do they repoſe in the ſleep of peace, when they indure both a puniſhment of loſs in the want of the ſight of God, and a puniſhment of ſenſe? how do they reſt in Chriſt, when they are perhaps in far greater torments than they in this life? <hi>whereas Thoſe who dye in the Lord reſt from their labours</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 13.</note>. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Though the prayer runs, <hi>that God would abſolve him from his ſins,</hi> yet ſtill there is no neceſſity, that there ſhould be a Purgatory; for thoſe prayers may ſuppoſe as you ſee many do, the Soul yet to be in ſuſpence, and in its paſſage to Gods tribunal, and that they uſe the <hi>commendatio ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae</hi> at the buriall, or <hi>Trentall</hi> which
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49882:103"/> they did, when the Soul juſt went out of the body, ſo that theſe prayers ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignifie a prevention of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than any mitigation or ending of it: or again theſe prayers may refer to the reſurrection, for it is not ſaid, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve him from the bond of his ſins, that he may be preſently releaſed from Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, but <hi>that in the glory of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection being raiſed among the Saints, he may breath again:</hi> and ſo we have ſuch a prayer in the <hi>Pontifical,</hi> which begins, <hi>Deus cui omnia vivunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that God would command the Soul of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to be received by the holy Angels, and carried into the boſome of Abraham his friend and be raiſed at the laſt day: and what ever faults by the deceit of the devil be incur'd, thou of thy pitty and mercy waſh away by forgiving them.</hi> Here is a prayer for pardon, but then 'tis at the reſurrection, and thus though there are prayers for pardon, yet ſtill they are no way reconcileable with their Doctrine. Thus I have finiſhed the <hi>conſiderations</hi> which at preſent I intend and (perhaps if occaſion offer it ſelf (may add more: my concluſion is a
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49882:104"/> 
               <hi>requeſt</hi> to thoſe who begin to entertain ſuch fair opinions of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, that they would not exchange their <hi>Religion,</hi> before they conſider, what they ſhall gain by the bargain: I ſee many who did not much minde to underſtand the <hi>duties</hi> of their own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, much leſs to practice them, are eaſily drawn over to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party, and when they live like <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> at leaſt to ſeem ſome body, they pretend to be <hi>Papiſts:</hi> I envy them not ſuch <hi>Proſelites,</hi> who add nothing to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of any ſide, but only number: nor do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e looſe any thing by ſuch <hi>Renega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's</hi> whoſe practice diſgraced their profeſſion: the Church is purer when the dregs are purged out: <hi>Rome</hi> had at firſt wanted men to inhabite it if <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> had not opened an <hi>Aſylum,</hi> and modern <hi>Rome</hi> would not be ſo much repleniſhed, if there were not a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to ſhelter ſuch converts: 'tis hardly any matter what religion men profeſs if their practice be not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though they glory in their multitudes, yet many who ſeem to be of their religion, would prove (if they
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:49882:104"/> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted) of none at all. There are others well meaning perſons, who (as in Charity I muſt judge) are moved ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through affection to <hi>peace,</hi> or <hi>love</hi> to truth (as they think) to incline to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church: theſe I do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn for their love to peace: 'Tis a noble deſign in imitation of the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> to poure Oyle and Wine into the Churches wounds and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile brethren who are at od's: and God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orbid but we ſhould meet them for peaces ſake ſo far as we can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to piety and truth: but what benefit can we expect by our conceſſions? when they pretend (what ever we can judge from <hi>Scripture, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> or <hi>Antiquity)</hi> they cannot erre: yea the leaſt conceſſion that they have er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or can erre, oreturns their foundation, deſtroies the <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of their Church. What hopes to reclaim them to moderation, when thoſe who mediate for peace are looked on as enemies? <hi>Eras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Modrevius and Caſſander</hi> are in their account <hi>damnati authores</hi> and if they be not high flow'n <hi>Papiſts</hi> they
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:49882:105"/> account them (though they die in the communion of their Church) but only cloſe <hi>Heriticks.</hi> I do not condemn thoſe who are inquiſitive after truth, and ready to imbrace that which is attended with ſutable motives. To theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I offer theſe conſiderations, whether 'tis fit to adhere to that Church which requires all to believe thoſe Doctrines, as neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which are uncertain, and dubious? to imbrace thoſe for <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which are not ſuch? to receive thoſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> rites for wholſome and good, of which many are vain and fooliſh, and cannot be excuſed from <hi>Superſtition?</hi> Let them conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be fit to adhere to that Church, whoſe ſacred Offices contain many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths and impieties? and <hi>Laſtly,</hi> whoſe very prayers do in many things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict their avowed Doctrine? he that can ſwallow down ſuch conſiderations and turn <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> has (as I may judg) bidden adiew to his reaſon, as well as Religion.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49882:105"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
